<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A treatise of self-judging, in order to the worthy receiving of the Lords Supper. Together with a sermon of the generall day of judgement. / By Anthony Burgesse pastor of Sutton-Coldfield in Warwickshire.</title>
            <author>Burgess, Anthony, d. 1664.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1658</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 148 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 124 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77851</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B5661</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1904_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209997</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868839</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868839</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170542</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77851)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170542)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 236:E1904[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A treatise of self-judging, in order to the worthy receiving of the Lords Supper. Together with a sermon of the generall day of judgement. / By Anthony Burgesse pastor of Sutton-Coldfield in Warwickshire.</title>
                  <author>Burgess, Anthony, d. 1664.</author>
                  <author>Burgess, Anthony, d. 1664. Demonstration of the day of judgement against atheists &amp; hereticks.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 148, [12], 70 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.H. for T. Underhill at the Anchor, and M. Keinton at the Fountain, in Pauls Church-yard.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1658.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"A demonstration of the day of judgement" has separate title page dated 1657, separate register and pagination.</note>
                  <note>Page ² [2] bears order to print.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "8ber" [i.e. October].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Acts XVII, 31 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Judgement Day --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Corinne Vieracker</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Corinne Vieracker</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170542:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TREATISE OF SELF-JUDGING, In order to the Worthy Receiving OF THE Lords Supper.</p>
            <p>Together with a SERMON OF THE Generall DAY OF JUDGEMENT.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Anthony Burgeſſe</hi> Paſtor of <hi>Sutton-Coldfield</hi> in <hi>Warwickshire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J.H.</hi> for <hi>T. Underhill</hi> at the Anchor, and <hi>M. Keinton</hi> at the Fountain, in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1658.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:170542:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:170542:2"/>
                  <head>TO THE READER.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>READER,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He ſubject of this ſhort Trea iſe, (which for the comprehenſiveneſs and fruitfulneſs of it, might have ſwelled into a bigger Volumn) is <hi>Self-judging:</hi> The frequent commands for which in Scripture, as alſo the excellency, uſefulneſs, dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty and contrariety of it to fleſh and blood, which loveth to ſay, Soul take thy eaſe, do all proclaim the great mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb facs="tcp:170542:3"/> and importance there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; yea it may be juſtly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, that the neglect of this duty is the cauſe of miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriage and apoſtacy in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny profeſſors. Certainly <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin,</hi> when he had enlarged himſelf about that curious and exact point, wherein the temporary believer, and the truly godly differ, granting that <hi>ſimili ferè ſenſu affici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>untur,</hi> they feel almoſt the ſame things with one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, yet addeth, that in the hypocrite this ſenſe of divine things is not ſo radicated, it is alſo more confuſed, then what is in the godly, but here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they are deceived in their experiences, and one reaſon is, becauſe ſlothfulneſs doth
<pb facs="tcp:170542:3"/> ſo far poſſeſs them, <hi>ne cor ſuum probè ut par erat ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aminent,</hi> lib. <hi>3.</hi> Inſtit. cap. <hi>2.</hi> par. <hi>12.</hi> that they do not ſo throughly examine their heart, as is fit they ſhould. Some Heathens, as <hi>Pytha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goras</hi> &amp; <hi>Seneca,</hi> have made Eſſaies upon this duty: The Jeſuites alſo in their Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctates of devotion do much commend it; but the pillar and cloud that we have in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cripture, is only able to guide us in this wilderneſs: They only can manage this work with ſpiritual profici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency, who through an holy habit, have their ſenſes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed to diſcern between good and evil. For ſeeing there are three different
<pb facs="tcp:170542:4"/> principles may be working in our hearts, Nature in its im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement, The Devil with his deluſions, The Spirit of God, and that either in a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon way, ſuch as hypocrites and reprobates may attain unto, or in a peculiar, diſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minating way, which the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere do only partake of; what heavenly skill, what godly prudence is required to make a diſtinction herein, to diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence what is of nature or the devil, from the Spirit of God; yea to go further, and to diſcern what is of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God in a common way, and what in a ſpecial way: Such that can do this, muſt be like thoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Benjamites, <hi>Judg. 20.16. that could ſling
<pb facs="tcp:170542:4"/> ſtones at an hairs breadth, and not miſs.</hi> In the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract of this diſcourſe I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider this duty more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, as it is a neceſſary pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parative to the Ordinance of the Lords Supper, for this was the occaſion of faſtning upon this ſubject at firſt. My Method in handling of this Point, is for the moſt part, poſitive; waving con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies, even when the matter did ſeem to call for it. As <hi>pag. 126, 127.</hi> I affirm, <hi>That ſuch who are ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally dead, cannot put forth gracious actings at the Lords Supper, or ſpiritually eat and drink, ſo that they receive no heavenly nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment thereby;</hi> not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring
<pb facs="tcp:170542:5"/> upon the Controverſie, <hi>Whether the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per be a converting Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance,</hi> or not, being ſatisfied in this, That that Ordinance was not inſtituted, either for the exhibition, or obſignation of the firſt, and radical, or fundamental grace, but doth wholly preſuppoſe it: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I think <hi>Aquinas</hi> ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Orthodoxally in this, <hi>Comment. In cap. 11. ad Corinth. Epiſt. 1<hi rend="sup">a</hi> Lecti 7<hi rend="sup">a</hi>,</hi> who making this objection to himſelf, <hi>That Chriſt is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in this Sacrament, now he is a ſpiritual Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian, &amp; that not the whole, but the ſick need ſuch an one:</hi> He anſwereth, <hi>That this Sacrament declareth
<pb facs="tcp:170542:5"/> nouriſhment, and therefore none do receive the benefit thereof, but ſuch who live the life of grace, yet we muſt add that ſinners, if humbled, and of broken hearts, ought to addreſſe themſelves to that Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance for the ſealing of the pardon of their ſins, to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viate that error in Popery, which denieth remiſſion of ſins to be vouchſafed in the right uſe thereof.</hi> Again, pag. <hi>128, 129.</hi> I declare <hi>That ſuch who have competent knowledge, and are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blameable in their lives, are by Church-officers to be admitted to this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, though happly not internally ſanctified.</hi> Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:170542:6"/> is the Church-officer to attend to that, but the command and order of Chriſt, not launching into the Controverſie of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſiveneſſe of the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of Ordinances, or the qualifications of Church-members, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſcing in that which <hi>Ames</hi> anſwereth to <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> Bellar. Enerv. tom. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>1.</hi> de Sacram. qu <hi>3.</hi> (who obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, That if Sacraments were the ſeals of grace, a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter could not baptize any, unleſs he knew he were ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, leſt he ſhould apply the ſeal to a falſhood,) <hi>That Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters are not to admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Sacraments according to their private knowledge
<pb facs="tcp:170542:6"/> or opinion, but according to the command of God.</hi> Let me alſo advertiſe thee, that becauſe of the conſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinity of the matter, there is annexed a Sermon of the day of Judgement, ſelf-judging being a ſpeciall means to prevent that dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full judgemen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in that great day. The great Prophet of his people teach thee to profit and make theſe neceſſary inſtructions effectual to thy ſouls good.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Anthony Burgeſſe.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="errata">
                  <pb facs="tcp:170542:7"/>
                  <head>ERRATA.</head>
                  <p>PAg. 12. lin. 7. r. <hi>Cyprian, Inde ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat actus noſtri ratio, unde ordo &amp; origo ſurrexit.</hi> p. 19. l. 18. r. <hi>Ancient did.</hi> p. 43. l. 5. r. <hi>deſultorious.</hi> l. 3. r. <hi>true gold.</hi> l. 14. dele <hi>mettall.</hi> p. 49. l. 20. r. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. p. 64. l. 19. r. <hi>renew.</hi> p. 82. l. 17. dele <hi>voluntary.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the Sermon of Judgement.</p>
                  <p>Pag. 9. l. 11. r. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. p. 36. l. 11. dele <hi>vertuous.</hi> p. 59. l. 20. r. <hi>is u.</hi> p. 64. l. 17. r. <hi>tu rides.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="treatise">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170542:7"/>
                  <head>A TREATISE of Self-judging, In order to the Worthy receiving the LORDS SUPPER.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>1 COR. 11.31.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>For if we would judge our ſelves, we ſhould not be judged.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Rom the 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi> verſe to the end of the Chapter,<note place="margin">Some ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons from S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                        <hi>Pauls</hi> Diſcourſe about the Lords Supper.</note> we may ſee <hi>Paul</hi> like a ſhining and burning light, with that <hi>Urim</hi> and <hi>Thummim</hi> upon him, as ſome expound it; light by his doctrinall informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:170542:8"/> burning, by his ſevere and ſharp reprehenſion. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, in a very terrible manner, as <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome;</hi> and all this, wholly about the Sacrament of the Lords Supper. Now although it would be too much, to analize and take notice of all the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, in this his Diſcourſe about the Lords Supper, yet I ſhall touch upon ſome general obſervations, and ſo bring you to the text. Firſt therefore take notice of the ſuddain and ſpeedy degeneracy of this Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> from Chriſts firſt inſtitution a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Sacrament: who would thinke that this
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:170542:8"/> Church being a garden of <hi>Pauls</hi> own planting, and he yet alive, that it ſhould be thus over-grown with weeds? As <hi>Paul</hi> of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrinalls, to the Church of <hi>Galatia,</hi> ſo here of practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calls, I wonder you are ſo ſoon removed from him that called you, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.6. You ſee a falſe Apoſtle, an heretical teacher could do more on a ſuddain to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert ſouls, then the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle in many years to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh them. That which other painfull Miniſters have with much difficulty bin a building many years, they can ſuddenly deſtroy. We may ſay of many Churches ſince Chriſts
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:170542:9"/> time, how is it that they have fallen off from that primitive purity and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly order, which was ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved by the Apoſtles.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Obſerve the devil and his inſtruments buſied in the corrupting of this or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, above any elſe. <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> obſerveth well, that there was not ſuch corruption about Baptiſm, as about this ordinance. Its true in after ages the corruptions both doctrinal and practical, were very great about both the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, but he began firſt with the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, as being that which is the higheſt Church-grace and favour.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:170542:9"/>3. The corruption about this ordinance was occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned by an humane inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, their <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, Their love-feaſts, which <hi>Jude</hi> mentioneth, ſaying, ſome were ſpots in their feaſts of charity, <hi>Jude</hi> 12. whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they were at firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted in imitation of the Jewes, or as ſome, of the Gentiles, who uſed to have their feaſts after their ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices, is doubted. The intent was to nouriſh and keep up love amongſt one another. Its judged by moſt, and <hi>Paul</hi> ſeemeth to make it probable, that they were before the Lords Supper, though <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome,</hi> and others, make
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:170542:10"/> them after: <hi>Maldonate</hi> and other Jeſuits, will by no means underſtand the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt by the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, but are peremptory, that neither Scripture, or the Fathers ever gave it ſuch a name. But <hi>Cauſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bon</hi> doth well chaſtiſe this impudency of theirs. For why ſhould the Apoſtle bring in the ſolemn inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of the Lords Supper at firſt, if their diviſions and prophanes did not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late to that, though occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned by their love-feaſts, whether the Apoſtle doth abſolutely condemne the very uſe of the love-feaſts, as being an humane inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution added to the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:170542:10"/> or the abuſe onely is likewiſe doubted. It is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for us, to ſee how unhappy theſe prooved in the iſſue, for they fell into diviſions &amp; factions, here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by making as it were ſo many parties: and withall, the poore were deſpiſed, and the rich they grew in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperate; and in theſe diſtempers they dared to proceed to this ordinance; for this it is, the Apoſtle though he had praiſed them in the beginning of the Chapter for keeping his order, yet here he could not do it, ſome holy order they kept, but not all.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 <hi>Obſ:</hi> That that Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:170542:11"/> which was appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Chriſt, not only as a ſeale of communion with him, but of believers a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt themſelves, was now abuſed, through the many ſchiſmes and divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions that were amongſt them, and made an occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of diſcord and ſtrife; and is not this ſadly to be laid to our hearts, that there are more breaches and rents about this ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, which yet is for communion, then any po nt in religion; how many doctrinall contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies, how many diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plinary controverſies, all tending to break love and union, by the ſymboles
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:170542:11"/> and ſeales of union, what diſpute about the order, about the communicants, about the benefits, the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments being by ſome made Idols, as in Popery, which cauſed a learned man to wiſh the word <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament</hi> had bin laid aſide, people co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiving ſome hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den vertue in the bread and wine by that name; and by othe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s deſpiſed, as by thoſe who ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y they are above ordinances, when yet we are to doe this in remembrance of Chriſt, till his coming, if we were ſure Chriſt were to come the next day, yet we might receive this ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance immediatly before.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:170542:12"/> The Socinians &amp; Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s doe debaſe them; The latter ſay, the whole doctrine of the reformed Church about the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, is <hi>nobis valde ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecta,</hi> is greatly ſuſpect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d of falſhood by us; and the former ſay, its only a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memoration of Chriſts death, ſo that there is no grace or benefit anew re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived; ev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> ſay they, as in the com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>oration of the Angels Paſsover in the Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>chall Lamb, there was no new deliverance vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafed: but the very inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of ſuch Elements, bread and wine, argue they a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e ſpirituall Alimony to the true receiver, onely
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:170542:12"/> theſe ſad diviſions hinder the bleſſed fruit thereof.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obſ:</hi> 5. That the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle in reformation of this abuſe, goe h to the o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>igi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll inſtitution, he decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth what he had received of Chriſt, <hi>viz.</hi> immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, for <hi>Paul</hi> was not a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the inſtitution of it, and indeed to reforme, is properly to bring a thing to its firſt forme or originall; we account what the Church did about the Sacraments when it came out of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, was reformation, though the Papiſts call it deformation; That which is reformat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on to one, is confuſion to another. Therefore the onely way
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:170542:13"/> to decide this is not cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, multitude, or as <hi>Stapleton,</hi> Eccleſiaſticall tradition, for that is as corrupt as any thing elſe, but divine inſtitution, as <hi>Cyprian, Vide, ſurgat altum noſtrum recte, unde ordo &amp; origo ſurrexit,</hi> let our acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ariſe from the ſame fountaine that inſtitutions themſelves d d, <hi>Eliſha</hi> powred ſalt in the ſpring, when the ſtreames were bitter; and about the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament it is to be obſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, that whereas many perſons are ſo importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate for antiquity and old cuſtomes in other things, when we can from Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and the Ancients for
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:170542:13"/> two or three hundred yeares after Chriſt, ſhew plainly how carefull they were that no ignorant and prophane perſon ſhould be admitted to this ordinance, then they w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll not hearken or yeild obedience: bring Antiquity for any ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition, or needleſſe cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, they are glad of it, but when for purity and godly order, they cannot digeſt it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obſ:</hi> 6. That God did very ſeverely puniſh theſe <hi>Corinthians</hi> for their diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der about the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per; <hi>For this cauſe</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> ver. 30.) <hi>many are ſick, weake, and dye.</hi> There was a common mortali ie,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:170542:14"/> (if not the plague) amongſt them. <hi>Paul</hi> indeed could by the guidance of Gods Spirit know that was the particular cauſe, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though we have not ſuch certain knowledge, yet we may with <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> reckon publick calamities upon a Land, as warre, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, &amp; plague, with other peſtilential diſeaſes to this ſin, as part. Certainly, we do not conſider, that this Sacrament-ſin is ſo highly provoking of God, when we doe not attribute our miſeries to this, at leaſt, as one cauſe among the reſt; and Gods judgments for this are the more to be obſerved, becauſe in the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:170542:14"/> New Teſtament this is the onely inſtance we have of a publick generall judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Indeed <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphira</hi> were ſtricken dead for lying againſt the holy Ghoſt, and <hi>Elymas</hi> blind, but here many, ſome whereof were godly and holy, were ſick, and others cut off with untimely deaths. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſeemeth to be an alluſion concerning Gods order about the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chal Lamb, which whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever did tranſgreſſe, was to be cut off.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. The Apoſtle there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to prevent all ſuch abuſes for the future, doth ſo forcibly informe about the unworthy receiving
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:170542:15"/> of this ordinance, That it hath left ſome impreſſion upon all Churches, to keep off thoſe that are dogs and ſwine, not to give this bread and pearle to ſuch, let them be Epiſcopall, (ſome of them at leaſt) Presbyteriall, or Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gationall. <hi>Hooker</hi> in his <hi>Poſthumus</hi> bookes of Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall Poli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, ſixth Booke, <hi>pag.</hi> 57. doth af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, that by the Church of <hi>England,</hi> Every noto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous offender was to be kept from that ordinance, and (which is remarkable) that all Miniſters had e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually power to do it.</p>
                  <p>The Socinians do highly preſſe the caſting out of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:170542:15"/> all evill perſons, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne the Evangelicall Churches for remiſsneſſe therein: yea, <hi>Eraſtus</hi> one of the firſt that troubled the Church about the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of perſons to the Sacrament, doth yet often profeſſe that he onely un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtands ſuch ſinners to be admitted, as publickly repent of their ſinnes, and promiſe amendment. He maketh it a great injury done to him, as if his opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion were that all who name themſelves <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> yea though neither willing, nor thinking to depart from their evill wayes, were to be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, therefore profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:170542:16"/> he ſo diſputeth of theſe points, as that he would have the cuſtome of their Church obſerved, <hi>Eraſt. Contr: Theſ. lib.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. And he ſpeaketh expreſsly againſt the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſcuous admiſſion of all, without any examination. It is an injury and a ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumny, he ſaith, to charge that opinion on him, <hi>lib.</hi> 6. <hi>pag.</hi> 34. Certainly, theſe thunderbolts of <hi>Paul</hi> have made deep impreſſions up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on mens hearts, though otherwiſe not willing to be affected with much ſtrictneſſe herein.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. We may obſerve, it is a bleſſed and happy thing that <hi>Paul</hi> did thus
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:170542:16"/> by the Spirit of God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large himſelfe about the inſtitution of this ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance; for although three Evangeliſts relate the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of it, (<hi>John</hi> onely omitting it) yet <hi>Paul</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of a fourth Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt, doth with much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largement make mention of it; for who could have gathered ſuch concluſions as <hi>Paul</hi> did from the meer inſtitution, had not the Spirit of God immediatly guided him, ſo that theſe very ſins of the <hi>Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> we may as the ancient <hi>Adams</hi> ſin, call them <hi>feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces culpae;</hi> for their corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions gave occaſion to <hi>Paul</hi> for ſuch a large and pithy
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:170542:17"/> amplification about it.</p>
                  <p>And therefore as it was a mercy to the Church, that many hereſies aroſe, even in the Apoſtles daies, which made them ſpeake ſo diſtinctly and clearely againſt them, as about Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification by the works of the Law, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Yea the doubtings of the Apoſtles in many particulars, is the cauſe why we doe not doubt now about the ſame things. Which made one ſay, <hi>Plus debeo Thomae du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitanti, quam Petro creden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti,</hi> I owe more to <hi>Thomas</hi> doubting, then <hi>Peter</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving. As (I ſay) the event of ſuch hereſies or doubts was in mercy to
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:170542:17"/> the Church, ſo diſorders and corruption in the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline of the Church, did provoke the Apoſtle to ſpeake ſo much about this ordinance as he doth. And it was <hi>Caſaubons</hi> good wiſh, that men had been more induſtrious to bring in the Primitive good or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in Church-diſcipline, then ſubtilly to diſpute without Scripture-light in many controverſal points, this would have bin more acceptable to God, <hi>Exer.</hi> 16. <hi>pag.</hi> 396.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly; Obſerve amongſt the many arguments for our right approaching, this in my text is none of the meaneſt, wherein we may conſider.</p>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:170542:18"/>
                  <p>Firſt, the duty ſuppoſed, with the object of it, if we would judge our ſelves, what the word <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, doth imply, will appear in the doctrine <hi>Grotius</hi> think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth this place may not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitly be expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded of their publick Church-cenſures, as if the Apoſtles meaning were, if you had godly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline, &amp; this were faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully put in order, this would prevent Gods judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; for he thinketh by the ſeverall factions that were, the diſcipline of the Church lay proſtrate; but I will go in the moſt gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall interpretation of it, and ſo the words may be conſidered, either in the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:170542:18"/> 
                     <hi>Theſi,</hi> as a Theologicall Aphoriſme, That ſelf-judging, will prevent Gods judging of us in all caſes; or elſe in <hi>Hypotheſi,</hi> in the particular, as it doth relate to the Sacrament. Hence <hi>Eraſmus</hi> renders it in the paſt ſence, If we had jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged our ſelves, we had not been judged of the Lord. I ſhall take in both theſe conſiderations.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, There is the benefit propoſed, or diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered upon our ſelf-judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, we ſhould not be jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged. The Apoſtle ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth here of believers as well as wicked men, yea chiefly of believers, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he addeth, verſ. 32.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:170542:19"/> 
                     <hi>When we are judged, we are chaſten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d of the Lord, that we may not be condemned with the world.</hi> The world and the godly are directly oppoſite; here are then three doctrines in this text, as the naturall off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring of it.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, <hi>That ſelf-judging, preventeth Gods judging.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, <hi>God doth judge even his own people for their ſins.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thirdly, <hi>The ſins which God judgeth them for, are not only morall, groſſe ſins, but their ordinance-ſins, their Sacrament-ſins, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted againſt poſitive in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions.</hi> For the firſt; <hi>He that judgeth himſelf,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:170542:19"/> taketh the way to prevent Gods judging of him.</hi> What our Saviour ſaies of judging of others, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.1. <hi>Judge not leſt ye be judged,</hi> is clean contrary here: Judge your ſelves, and that ſeverely, imparti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, elſe God will judge you: You ſee there muſt be judging, if you do not judge your ſelves here, God will judge hereafter; if here be not a judgement of diſcuſſion, in hell there will be a judgement of condemnation. This ſelf-judging it is the marrow, and ſoul of all Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; for want of this it is that there are ſo many hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites and Apoſtates in
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:170542:20"/> Religion; for want of this, that there are ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Phariſaicall, and ſelf-righteous men; If this duty were more practiſed, there would be more truth and ſincerity in the waies of godlineſs: ſo that in this very thing the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane and the godly man part; the Phariſee and the true believer are divided; the hypo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rite and the true Saint differ: they may both pray, they may both abound in gifts and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largements, they may both be frequent in the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, but the one judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth himſelf, and the other doth not, or cannot, or dare not, he is afraid to
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:170542:20"/> ſearch into himſelf; ſo that this is a duty required of us in our whole life, but eſpecially upon ſome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary occaſions, as here in this <hi>Sacramentall Adminiſtration.</hi> Had <hi>Jehu</hi> judged himſelf, had <hi>Judas</hi> judged himſelf, they had not been ſuch ſcandals in Religion.</p>
                  <p>But let us rip up, as it were, and diſcover this great and weighty duty of ſelf-judging; and herein we are to know, that many things are <hi>antecedent</hi> to it, ſome things <hi>conſtituent</hi> of it, ſome things <hi>concomitant</hi> of it, and ſome things <hi>conſequent</hi> from it; and all theſe manifeſted, will
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:170542:21"/> make us able to judge of this ſelf-judging.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">What things are antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to ſelf-judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</note>To the Antecedent or introductory things we referre theſe particulars.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. A man muſt erect a tribunal and barre, as it were, in his own heart, and aſſume to himſelf a ſuperiority and dominion as it were, over himſelf, for thus all judgement is exerciſed; he that is a Judge in that act is a ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour: Now in man, we may conſider him as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned in his conſcience by the word, and herein ſupplying Gods place: So that conſcience is not only a witneſs, but a Judge, and that is the reaſon why a
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:170542:21"/> man may not do any thing againſt conſcience, though otherwiſe, he is indeed bound to lay aſide his er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, but he muſt not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict it, becauſe it is a Judge in Gods room; he may and muſt many times go againſt his affections, his will, his inclinations, but never againſt his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. The very Heathen could ſay, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Conſcience is a God to every man:</hi> it is in Gods room; yet becauſe it is an inferiour judge, ſubject to errour, when it appeareth God the ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour Judge doth counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the contrary, then that ceaſeth and hath no
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:170542:22"/> further authority. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. The Apoſtle ſpeaking of the Heathens, ſaid, <hi>their conſciences did accuſe, or excuſe;</hi> here was judging then, and that by ſome ſuperiority. Now this is much to be obſerved, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe naturally we are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to ſet up ſuch a Court in our breaſt, we think we ſhall bring our ſelves under too much ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very; we cannot then, though but a little while, turn aſide into any vain thoughts, or any looſe pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes, but we muſt be ſummoned to this court preſently; men would be uncontrolled in their luſts, and therefore to aſſume a
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:170542:22"/> ſuperiority over a mans ſelf, to make a mans ſelf the delinquent, the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, to ſhew no pity, no compaſſion to his ſinnes, this is very difficult. No wonder men do not love Church-Diſcipline, for they cannot abide heart-diſcipline, ſoul order; they do not love to ſet up a ſpiritual court the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e to arraign themſelves, their convinced ſelves, againſt their delinquent ſelves, their inlightned ſelves, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their corrupt ſelves; yet this muſt be, where ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f-judging is: As long as thou art afraid to leave thy luſts, or ſin keeps thee in ſlavery, thou wilt never
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:170542:23"/> erect a court in thy own heart to condemn them.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The ſecond thing an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecedent is knowledge and underſtanding, for if thou ſet up ſuch a court in thy breaſt, and there be no Scripture wiſdom to guide thee, here will be much falſe judgement: how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times doth the true believer bear falſe witneſs againſt himſelf, condemn himſelf falſly for an hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite, for a caſtaway, for one left by God: and on the other ſide, doth not the phariſaical man clear him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, ſay all is well, acquit himſelf becauſe his waies are clean in his own eyes; and all this is, becauſe
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:170542:23"/> there is not that heavenly light to guide us in this ſelf-judging. Now there is a twofold knowledge muſt go before we can paſs any true ſentence about our ſelves. Firſt, A know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of our ſelves; that which the very Heathens have admitted as a funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall truth, and a divine Oracle, <hi>E coelo deſcendit;</hi> but we ſee neither Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, no nor ſuch as reade and know the Scripture, can perform this, while unregenerated <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. <hi>Paul</hi> did wholly miſtake him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; <hi>Nicodemus</hi> did not know himſelf; for this knowledge muſt be of our ſtate by nature, in the firſt
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:170542:24"/> place, that is a myſtery: How many hereticks deny any ſuch natural pollution, whereas the greateſt part of our evil lieth in this. <hi>Job</hi> and <hi>David</hi> did go from actual ſins to this of their nature, as the ſpring of all their evil, and for which they ought moſt to humble themſelves; and when we throughly know this wretched and damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble eſtate of our nature, then able we are to know our ſins paſt and preſent, eſpecially our deareſt ſins, our own iniquities: So that by this it appeareth, that much ſpiritual skill, and heavenly wiſdom is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to this ſelf-judging,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:170542:24"/> becauſe there muſt be ſo much ſelf-knowing. Alas wilt thou go to judge thy heart, that knoweſt not the depths, or the deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe of it! Did not <hi>David,</hi> though a godly man, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19. who had much illumination &amp; ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification, cry out, <hi>Who can underſtand his errours? cleanſe me from ſecret ſins;</hi> that corruption I do not know, I cannot diſcover. If therefore thou wilt ſet upon this duty, get more knowledge of thy ſelf, let in more light into thy breſt, elſe there will many ſerpentine luſts lie craw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in thy heart, that thou wilt never diſcover: If a
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:170542:25"/> godly man hardly know himſelf, how can a wicked man, who is wholly blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with ſelf-love. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, There muſt be a know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ge of the rule, the law, by which we are to judge our ſelves; as there muſt be light within, ſo with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out; as we muſt try ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits and doctrines by the word, ſo our hearts and actions by it, otherwiſe we ſhall foully miſtake: it is of great conſequence what rule you judge your ſelves by. The Scripture it may be condemneth that as loathſom, as abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable, which is glorious in thy eyes: The Scripture will tell thee that is no
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:170542:25"/> grace, no godlineſs, which thou thinkeſt will carry thee to heaven. Moſt men judge of themſelves by falſe rules; why is mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, why are duties, gifts, opinions, made grace to ſome men, reſting upon them? but becauſe they judge not by the rule; you muſt then be acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with Gods Word, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply that to thy heart, to thy life, to thy words: you muſt not bring the rule to you, making the Scripture for thy life, as heretiques do for their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions, wreſt it, poſſeſſing thy ſelf firſt with ſuch thoughts, &amp; apprehending the Scripture <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>very where
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:170542:26"/> ſpeaking to that purpoſe: So neither multitude, or the cuſtom of others is a rule to judge our ſelves by, yea on the contrary we are to ſay, <hi>Argumentum peſſimi turba,</hi> the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude is an argument of evil; and <hi>nunquid mali fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ci,</hi> what evil have I done, when all commend me. What do you more than others, ſaid our Saviour, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.47. but above all things we muſt not be a rule and a law to our ſelves, to make our own wils the Bible to walk by, and our own hearts the Scripture. The Scriptu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e ſpeaks notably, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.12. <hi>They meaſured them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:170542:26"/> by themſelves,</hi> they never looked upon better then themſelves. Amongſt blind men and deaf men, they that have any uſe of thoſe ſenſes, though much imperfect, are admired; ſo that in this ſelf-judging it is dangerous to make our own hearts the accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer and the judge, for then all will be well. This makes the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> incurable, that ſhe will acknowledge no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther judge but her ſelf. Thus when we judge of our ſelves by our own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largements, impulſes, reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, as the Illuminiſts and others do, theſe can never judge righteous
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:170542:27"/> judgement. Tradition on the Popiſh ſide, and Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations on the other ſide, have made the Scriptures authority void: but if thou wouldſt judge right, keep to this rule.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. There is required an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecedently to this ſelf-judging, compoſedneſſe and quietneſſe of ſpirit: The heart muſt caſt out all diſtracting turbulent workings of ſoul, elſe it is no waies able to judge it ſelf: A man cannot ſee his face in the water that is ſtirred and moved up and down. Therefore the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt ſaith, <hi>Pſal</hi> 4.4. <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mune with your heart upon your bed and be ſtill.</hi> How
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:170542:27"/> can that man, who is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies in a throng of bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe, in a croud of diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting thoughts, ever be able to paſſe ſentence upon himſelf. Therefore remove all diſquietneſs, all diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bances of ſoul; be as if there were nothing in the world, but God and thy own ſoul together, as <hi>Abraham</hi> left his beaſt and other things at the bottom of the hill, and went up to God alone. It's <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> rule, <hi>Anima ſedendo</hi> and <hi>quieſcendo fit ſapiens,</hi> A quiet ſedate frame of ſoul, is like wiping the duſt off the glaſſe to ſee our faces more clearly. In the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non Law the very ſitting
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:170542:28"/> is made requiſite to the validity of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e ſentence; that if the Judge do not <hi>ſedendo</hi> pronounce judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, it is void, becauſe it implyeth he is in ſome paſſion and commotion when he riſeth up, or ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth himſelf many waies.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. There muſt not only be a quiet ſeda<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e frame of ſoul, but there muſt be an a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tentive, fixed, and ſetled meditation of the heart in this work; ſo that ſelf-judging can never be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed without medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. This duty of medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, as it is commended in the Scripture, ſo it is very ſeldom practiſed by believers; there is not the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:170542:28"/> leaſt ſinne lurking in the ſoul, but meditation would finde and ſearch it out. Alas thy light, inconſtant deſulphurous thoughts, which are like a fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſh of lightning, theſe will never go to the bottom of thy ſoul. Hence this ſelf-judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is in equivalent expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, called ſearching and trying, as the Artificer doth cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>terfeit from gold mettall; or as the woman took a candle, and ſwept the houſe to finde her loſt groat. Meditation is the ſoul in paraphraſe, whereas ſhort ejaculations, are but the ſoul in an epitome, or in characters. It is a ſhame for us Proteſtants to ſee
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:170542:29"/> how much Jeſuitical de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion both commends and practiſeth this work of meditation; inſomuch that <hi>Suarez</hi> ſaid, he prized that part of the day, which was for the examination and ſcrutiny of his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, above all the time of his ſtudy, wherein he prepared ſo many volumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous books; and we are ſeldom or never in this duty.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, The work of God, even his efficacious grace is above all required antecedently, to inable us to this ſelf-judging; if we cannot do the leaſt good, or think the leaſt good thought without his grace,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:170542:29"/> how much leſſe this which is one of the greateſt and weightieſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. We know not what to pray, or how to pray without Gods Spirit, ſo neither what to judge, or how to judge, unleſſe God aſſiſt us in it. This made <hi>Paul</hi> ſay contrary to my text, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.3 <hi>I judge not my ſelf;</hi> What, did not <hi>Paul</hi> examine himſelf, &amp; watch over himſelf? yes he did, leſt he ſhould become a caſtaway, but he dared not to judge himſelf with a ſententiall abſolution of himſelf, as from and of himſelf; Why? becauſe <hi>it is God that judgeth.</hi> So then, unleſſe God who
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:170542:30"/> knoweth our hearts bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then we do, who ſeeth more pride, vanity, rotten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in thy ſoul, then thou canſt, unleſs he inable thee; thou maiſt be an <hi>Hazaell,</hi> when thou thinkeſt thy ſelf a Saint. Would <hi>Peter</hi> have ſpoken ſo preſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, if God had made his own heart known to him at that time?</p>
                  <p>In the next place let us conſider, what is formally conſtituent of this ſelf-judging,<note place="margin">What is formally conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent of this ſelf-judging.</note> and that lie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h in theſe things:</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Examination, explo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and diligent diving into our hearts. The Greek word is uſed ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times for diſputation and
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:170542:30"/> doubting, which is a kind of further ſearching into a thing; then at firſt appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, and truly this is neceſſary for our hearts, becauſe they are ſo deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full above all things. Thy principles, thy aims, thy ends, thy motives, and all the ſecret workings of thy ſoul, who can find out, but by diligent ſearching. The heart is like the ſea, though the waters are calm above ſometimes, yet there are many rocks, and ſeveral monſters under the waters. Therefore thou muſt ſearch and again ſearch, it may be thou art not yet come to the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom of thy heart for all thy duties.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb n="48" facs="tcp:170542:31"/>2. There is required not only examination, but di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcerning, and ſeparation of the vile from the pretious, of making a difference, between what is of God in thee, and what of the devil in thee; what is of the fleſh, and what is of the Spirit; for the meaning is not, as if a Chriſtian ſhould be alwaies ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and examining, and prying upon his ſoul, wearying himſelf in laby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinths of doubts and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexities, but he muſt be able to make a ſeparation. Thus the Apoſtle, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.9, 10. prayeth they might <hi>abound in all judgement,</hi> which was ſeen by <hi>appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:170542:31"/> the things that are excellent:</hi> and <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.14. ſome are ſaid to have <hi>their ſenſes exerciſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween good and evil:</hi> we ſee the hypocrite, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate may go farre: we ſee there are many that do doctrinally diſpute, that the work of grace is of the ſame <hi>ſpecies</hi> in a tempora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry believer and one rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerated; yea many diſpute, it's impoſſible to know whether we be in the ſtate of grace or no: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there is required this eagle-eye, for from that bird do ſome derive the word <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Oh then be thus wiſely qualified, as to be able upon thy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:170542:32"/> to take the droſſe from the gold, to winnow the chaff from the wheat, and ſo to ſeparate thy waies from the moſt refi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned paths of any hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. It's required, that up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſinne diſcovered, we ſhould paſſe ſentence of condemnation upon our ſelves; that as God will have at the day of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, a judgement of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſion, and then of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation to the wicked, ſo ſhould we: And this is the greateſt thing in this duty; if we would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn our ſelves, ſaying, Lord we are worthy of all thy curſes, of all thy wrath,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:170542:32"/> of all thy anger; this would prevent Gods judging of us. <hi>David</hi> thus judged himſelf often; but our ſelf-love, our ſelf-flattery is ſuch, that we are unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to ſentence our ſelves as loſt &amp; damned wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es. As <hi>Paul</hi> had the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of death, ſo we ſhould have of condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon our ſelves; and this is the way to have it repealed, to come to God, as they did to the King of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> with a rope about their necks.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, This judging is in a voluntary taking of all ſhame upon our ſelves; we judge our ſelves to mourn, to weep, we judge
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:170542:33"/> our ſelves to ſhame, and to an holy revenge upon our ſelves, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.11. <hi>What indignation, what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge:</hi> This was that pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance the Church of God did exerciſe it ſelf with in antiquity; for in groſſe ſcandalous ſinnes, ſuch as did offend the Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he that did truly judg himſelf for his ſins, could have no reſt, till he did publiquely confeſſe his ſin, and ſhame himſelf with tears, in the face of the Church. Indeed after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards this way was abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and Officers of the Church took upon them to injoyn penance, and to make new Sacraments a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:170542:33"/> it, but at firſt there was only this way of their repentance and ſelf-judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, a voluntary giving of God glory, and ſhaming themſelves; and this is the duty ſtill of all ſuch pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique groſſe ſinners, that do offend the Church. Thus they came to <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> publiquely <hi>confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing their ſins,</hi> Matth. 3.6. And thoſe who uſed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull arts, <hi>came and burnt their books,</hi> though of a great value, <hi>before Paul, Act.</hi> 19.19. It is not ſhame, or peoples talk, or any ſuch carnal conſideration, could hold them in, when their hearts were truly broken, and if ſuch Church-diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:170542:34"/> were in uſe, would there be ſo much bold, and impudent prophanneſſe as is every where? If they were called upon, as <hi>Joſhua</hi> to <hi>Achan,</hi> to <hi>give glory to God,</hi> Joſh. 7.19. they would not then preſſe to Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments without a wedding garment, yea with goar blood of their ſins upon them; but would rather with the leper ſtand aloof off, crying out, <hi>I am un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean, unclean:</hi> and with another, <hi>Calcate me inſipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum ſalem,</hi> trample on me as unſavoury ſalt: They would not then rage at the Miniſter, and ſay, the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments are their dues, but would acknowledge
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:170542:34"/> publike ſhame and ſorrow was due to them: They would not preſſe to make us guilty of unworthy gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, while they are of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy receiving: <hi>Et dum ſe ſolvere cupiunt ligare Sacerdotem,</hi> as <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſpeaketh excellently, while they ſeek to loſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, to binde the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter. But it is not all the books, all the arguments in the world that will do this, it muſt be an humble heart, truly contrite before God. To hear men cavil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling whether Godly order be <hi>Jure Divino,</hi> when the world knoweth their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanneſſe, their impiety is not <hi>Jure Divino,</hi> may
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:170542:35"/> make us conclude, that it is not arguments, or books, but an humble, ſelf judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing heart, that muſt decide this controverſie.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of this ſelf-judging.</note>The next thing is the Concomitants: And fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt, ſelf-judging is accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with exalting and ſetting up of God, as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> Pſal. 5.4. <hi>Thou maieſt overcome when thou art judged.</hi> So much as the ſoul judgeth it ſelf, ſo much it cleareth God. O God my perdition is of my ſelf, if temporal, if ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual judgements fall up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me, I muſt clear thee, I cannot charge the holy God fooliſhly. Thus man is low, and God is ſet up.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb n="57" facs="tcp:170542:35"/>2. This is accompanied with ſincerity, and ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ity. <hi>Examine me and try me,</hi> ſaid <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 26.2. The ſincere heart is wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling every ſecret corner of his ſoul ſhould be ſearched into, but the hypocrite of all duties, cannot abide this ſelf-judging, he will never ſay, <hi>Even my ſon Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nathan ſhall die.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. It is accompanied with much ſhame and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenting of ſoul: He is judged, even as a poor ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefactor is judged, that bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly laments his miſery, and therefore the whole work of converſion is in this ſelf-judging.</p>
                  <p>The laſt thing, are the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:170542:36"/> Conſequents of ſelf-judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;<note place="margin">The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences of this ſelf-judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</note> which are,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. A readineſſe to every duty, to every holy per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance. He that hath judged himſelf faithfully, he cryeth out with <hi>Paul, What wilt thou Lord have me to do</hi> Thou haſt never throughly &amp; deeply judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thy ſelf, if thou canſt not pull out thy right eye.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. He doth renounce all his own righteouſneſs, fly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing alone to Chriſt, and ſeeking for juſtification by him alone. The Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee did not judge himſelf, and ſo he ſaw not the need of Chriſt. <hi>We thus judge,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 Cor. 5.14. <hi>if Chriſt died for all, then all
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:170542:36"/> were dead, deſcende<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do ad coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum aſcenditur;</hi> by deſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing we aſcend to heaven.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. They are patient and humble under all thoſe chaſtiſements God layeth upon them for their ſins; they judge themſelves worthy of them, and hell it ſelf. <hi>Why ſhould a man complain of the puniſhment of his ſins,</hi> Lam. 3.39. Thus they accept of their pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. They have a deaf ear againſt all the cenſures and calumnies wicked men caſt upon them. They judge themſelves more then all the world doth, and for that heart corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which the world can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not know.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <pb n="60" facs="tcp:170542:37"/>5. This will make him a ſavoury, experimentall Chriſtian, he can tell how to ſpeak to the temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to the doubts of other mens hearts, and to the caſes of conſcience in god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men; by this duty con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly performed, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to have wonderfull skill in heart-work, he knoweth more then books can teach him, he cloſeth with a heart ſearching Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, he ſpeaks from the heart, to the heart of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, He doth not ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully cenſure others, he hath enough to do to judg himſelf; neither can he give way to uſeleſſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:170542:37"/> and opinions in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion: Oh this ſelf judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing will make a man avoid all theſe endleſſe queſtions that beget nothing but ſtrifes; therefore its ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent counſell to thoſe who ſpend their whole life in diſputes and opinions, to be more acquainted with ſelf judging, and thou wilt finde thy own heart will help thee to work e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough: thou wilt finde errours, luſts, ſuch combats and rebellions in the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cticall way of powerfull godlineſſe, that thou wilt be amazed to ſee how men can take up ſo much time abroad, and keep ſo little at home.</p>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:170542:38"/>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Some practical Coralla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries or Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions from the truth pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed.</note>Let us adde ſome Corallaries, or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions from the truth premiſed.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That a natural unrege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate man, cannot judge himſelf, he wants all the forementioned Antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents; ſo that in this ſenſe it is true, <hi>The ſpiritual man judgeth all things,</hi> 1 Cor. 2.15. Can a beaſt judge, what the reaſon of a man is?</p>
                  <p n="2">2. This ſelf-judging is not oppoſite to an Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical, Goſpel frame, nor to the Spirit of Adoption; you may think this is too legal, this will incourage doubtings, &amp; baniſh fears; certainly the Apoſtle did
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:170542:38"/> not intend to prejudice grace, or to take the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians</hi> off from Chriſt, while he preſſeth this duty.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. This ſelf-judging though a duty, yet is wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be managed; we muſt not judge in our temptations, in our ſad thoughts, or when the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil diſtempers thy eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. This ſelf-judging is not to keep us in uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainties; but as we are to prove all things in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, yet not be Sce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pticks; we muſt hold faſt that which is good: ſo about our hearts we muſt judge, yet ſo as to make
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:170542:39"/> our Calling and Election ſure. This ſelf-judging muſt not oppoſe aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. No man can ſo judge himſelf, as to finde out all the naughtineſs of his heart; he cannot empty this Sea; if our hearts condemn us, God is grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then our hearts, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.20. God ſeeth more vileneſs and corruption in us, then we are able to finde out.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Under Gods judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or upon ſpecial ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches to him, we are to receive this duty. Therefore we are more ſolemnly to perform it at this time in approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:170542:39"/> to the Sacrament; for hereby we ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent Gods Judging of us.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Every Sacrament we have received God took notice of: God hath not forgot all thy former unworthy recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings. Thy old ſins, thy old formality, may be matter of trembling to thee: as <hi>Melancthon</hi> ſaid <hi>Totus cohorreſco,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>I am all in a trembling to think, how once in Popery I went boldly, and fell down before Images, worſhipping of them:</hi> ſo ſay, horrour ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth hold of me, to think how prophanely and ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reverently I once ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:170542:40"/> to this Table.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Judge thy ſelf, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the ſpecial grace and favour vouchſafed to the fit gueſt: the more thou judgeſt thy ſelf, Gods love will be the mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>com to thee: As the Centurion judged him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf unworthy that Chriſt ſhould come within his roof.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Judge thy ſelf, it may be this may recover the benefit of former Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments which was loſt: Godly men may receive unworthily, though in the ſtate of Grace, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe not in a Proxime preparation; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore receive the Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:170542:40"/> of Chaſtiſement, though not eternal Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation: Thus Self-judging then may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover the benefit of all by-paſt Sacraments.</p>
                  <div n="2" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="68" facs="tcp:170542:41"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Of Gods Judging and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing his own Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren for their ſins, with the Aggravation and mitigation of them com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with the ſins of others.</head>
                     <epigraph>
                        <q>
                           <bibl>
                              <hi>1 COR. 11.31.</hi>
                           </bibl>
                           <p>For if we would judge our ſelves, we ſhould not be judged.</p>
                        </q>
                     </epigraph>
                     <p>VVE proceed to the ſecond Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, which is very uſefull to awaken
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:170542:41"/> the Godly, and to make them walk with an holy fear, not abuſing the grace of God, and making his love an occaſion of ſin; which is, <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>t God doth Judge even his own peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple for their ſins:</hi> Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and Goſpel Grace doth not ſet Believers in ſuch a ſecure condition, that let them live how they will, Gods love will indulge all, God will take no notice of their ſins to chaſtiſe them for them. In the Text we have Gods judging of ſuch; for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it cannot be thought, that all who came irreverently to this Ordinance were truly
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:170542:42"/> Godly; ſo on the other ſide we cannot conclude none were; yea it is plain, that ſome of thoſe were truly holy, though offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God in their Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment-Sins, becauſe the Apoſtle addeth, <hi>verſe</hi> 32. <hi>When we are judged we are chaſtened of the Lord, that we may not be condemned with the world.</hi> This then being laid for a foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it is plain, that God judgeth his own people for their ſins. Now this word Judgement doth im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, that God is not only a Father to his People, but a Judge alſo, a Father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Judge: ſo that although as a Father he be merciful
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:170542:42"/> and pittiful, yet as a Judge he is ſevere, and will cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſe for ſin: this is notably expreſſed, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.12. <hi>If any man ſin, we have an Advocate with the Father:</hi> Though he be a Father, yet we need an Advocate upon our ſinning, even the Lord Chriſt. Though he is a tender Father, yet an Holy Judge alſo; and therefore doth God aſſume to himſelf ſuch tempered Relations, that his People might have ſuch a tempered and qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified frame of heart, that they might rejoyce with trembling, that they might love with reverence, that though they call on him
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:170542:43"/> as a Father, yet becauſe he is ſuch a father, they are to paſs the time of their ſojourning here in fear, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.17. Therefore obſerve what the Apoſtle addeth, if ye call him Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who without reſpect of perſons judgeth every man: if <hi>David</hi> though a man after his own heart? If <hi>Solomon</hi> though belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of the Lord do ſin againſt him, he will cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten them, and make them feel the bitterneſs of their fins as well as others; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though alwaies their is a great difference between the afflictions that are upon the Godly for their ſins, and thoſe which are
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:170542:43"/> upon the wicked. The wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d then in the Text doth ſuppoſe a real anger, and juſt diſpleaſure in God againſt his own peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple when they offend; for to judge is more then to chaſten: to chaſten is commonly made the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a Father; but to judge and to puniſh, the act of a judge; yet this latter God doth to his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending people; whether it be puniſhment, properly ſo taken, is afterward to be ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ken unto; we have the like paſſage, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.17. The time is come that judgement muſt begin at the houſe of God; here is judgement, and that to
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:170542:44"/> Gods houſe. It is true, the word judgement, even as to judge is uſed in ſeveral ſenſes in the Scripture, ſometimes for that ſtrict juſtice of God, whereby he will take notice of ſin to puniſh it, according to the utmoſt deſert of it. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this <hi>David,</hi> though a godly and juſtified man, doth earneſtly deprecate, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 143.2. <hi>Enter not into judgement with thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant,</hi> and the reaſon is full of weight; <hi>for in thy ſight no fleſh ſhall be juſtified:</hi> There is no holy man can ſtand in this judgement, if God be only as a Judge, and not a Father likewiſe, we are all damned men;
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:170542:44"/> but at other times judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is uſed for mercy, and moderation oppoſite to anger, as, <hi>Jer.</hi> 10.24. <hi>O Lord correct me, but with judgement, not in thine an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger;</hi> that is in modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, let my afflictions be medicinal, not deſtructive, <hi>Aliter ſecat Chirurgus, ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Lanius;</hi> he prayeth that God would let no more blood from him then may abate his diſeaſe, and wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken corruption within him, ſuitable to this, is that expreſſion, <hi>Ier.</hi> 30.11. Where God, though he threatens the Nations to make a full end of them by his anger, yet to <hi>Iſrael</hi> he ſaith, <hi>I will correct thee
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:170542:45"/> in meaſure or in judgement,</hi> he would not pour out all his wrath: Thus the godly have ſubmitted to Gods rebukes; <hi>Jeremiah</hi> doth not pray to be corrected, but it is his conceſſion and reſignation, <hi>If Lord I have provoked thee, and thou cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect me, let it not be in thy anger and hot diſpleaſure; for who can indure under that.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But in my Text, to <hi>judge,</hi> and <hi>judgement</hi> is not taken for moderation, or mercy, but f r ſeverity and afflictions, ariſing from Gods anger to his people, when they have ſinned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ga nſt him.</p>
                     <p>Let us lay open the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:170542:45"/> Doctrine; and firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, that there are two extream and dangerous errors<note place="margin">Two er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors to be avoided.</note> about this truth, and you muſt carefully avoid both theſe rocks: for firſt there is the <hi>Antinomian</hi> erring on the right hand, and they do ſo magnifie the grace of God in juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, they do ſo exalt the love of God in Chriſt to believers, that they ſay God never ſeeth any ſin in them, he is never angry with them; he is as well pleaſed with <hi>David</hi> in his Adultery, as when making his Penitential <hi>Pſalm:</hi> as well with <hi>Peter,</hi> denying Chriſt, as when weeping bitterly; but certainly
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:170542:46"/> this opinion may quickly fall from the head to kill the vitals of all holineſs; for if God doth not ſee ſin in me, why ſhould I ſee ſin in my ſelf? And if God be not angry with me for my offences, why ſhould I be angry and grieved at my ſelf, when I have fallen into any ſin; ſo that this opinion doth overthrow all thoſe commands which are made to the godly up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their falls, to repent, and to recover from their backſlidings, with broken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and bitterneſs of heart. As alſo it chargeth <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Peter,</hi> with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who have ſo bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bewailed their revolt
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:170542:46"/> from God with weakneſs, yea ſinfulneſs, troubling and grieving themſelves where they ought not. According to this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, God never chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth for ſin (as they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs it) but from ſin, that is, the afflictions which come upon the godly, do not ariſe from Gods anger for ſin paſt, only they are afflicted to prevent future. But the inſtance in my Text doth confute this; for theſe <hi>Corinthians</hi> being guilty of ſinfull approa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches to the Lords Table; it was becauſe of this ſin that God brought ſuch a general mortality amongſt them; for this cauſe, ſaith
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:170542:47"/> the Apoſtle, <hi>ver.</hi> 30. <hi>Many are ſick and weak</hi> not ſome, but many, and it was for this cauſe: It is true in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the afflictions Gods people have, are for the preventing of future cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, and to teach them not to ſin any more; yet withal they are ſharp ſtings for ſins paſt. Let not then the gracious heart delude himſelf, that becauſe he is in a ſtate of grace, he may therefore ſin and do what he liſt: let him remember what the Apoſtle ſaith, even in the perſon of the godly, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.29. <hi>For our God is a conſuming fire. Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> complaineth of his
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:170542:47"/> 
                        <hi>broken bones,</hi> and wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>h ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny tears and agonies of ſoul prayeth that God would reſtore his loving kindneſs to him, for he had loſt the ſence and feel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it. It is true the people of God are to grow up into the Spirit of Adoption, and to caſt out all tormenting fears; but they muſt diſtinguiſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Liberty and Licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſneſs, they muſt not under that pretence caſt out an holy trembling and a reverential fear leſt they offend God at any time. In the <hi>ſecond</hi> place, the Devil promoteth his Kingdom of darkneſs on the left hand, if he cannot
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:170542:48"/> on the right; therefore in Popery their is alſo cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Doctrine about this point, and inſtead of milk they wring till blood co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth; for they ſay, God doth not only judge his people for their ſins, though he hath pardoned the fault, but that he doth afterwards in a proper way puniſh them, and avenge himſelf in a way of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, which they are to ſatifie in reſpect of tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral puniſhments by ſome voluntary penalties either inflicted upon them, or voluntarily aſſumed. Thus when <hi>David</hi> hath his ſin pardoned, yet they ſay, the death of his childe was
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:170542:48"/> inflicted as a proper pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment to ſatisfie the juſtice of God: Chriſts blood takes away the guilt of ſin, but mans poenal exerciſes, muſt take away the temporal puniſhment. Thus by their diſtinctions they do greatly obſcure the Doctrine of Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which doth take off all the guilt of ſin, ſo that there remaineth properly no more puniſhment for ſin thus pardoned; I would not contend about the word puniſhment, I ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e Divines do uſe the word concerning thoſe afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which God layeth up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his people, only we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſay they are <hi>ultiones,</hi>
                        <pb n="84" facs="tcp:170542:49"/> they are not acts of ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance to the godly, as they are to the wicked, being of the ſame nature, though different in degree with the torments of hell to the damned. <hi>Calvin</hi> therefore doth diſtinguiſh between <hi>Judicium ultionis</hi> and <hi>Judicium caſtigationis,</hi> a judgement of revenge, and a judgement of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſement; the latter onely befall the godly, and if you ſay, why then doth the Scripture require hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation and repentance? Yea, <hi>Bellarmine</hi> urgeth my Text, <hi>to judge our ſelves,</hi> which he would have, to imply ſuch voluntary pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing of our ſelves,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:170542:49"/> through Faſting, and other duties, that thereby we may ſatisfie Gods juſtice, ſo as to remove the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral puniſhment.</p>
                     <p>I anſwer, the Apoſtle doth not uſe the word <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, when he ſpeaks of our duty, but <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, which is to examine and ſearch our ſelves, to ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate the evil from the good, upon diſcuſſion of our ſelves to be greatly humbled, and loathing of our ſelves for our ſins N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t that theſe duties are to ſatisfie Gods Juſtice, but onely they are the way, wherein God alone will communicate mercy. Thus you ſee how the
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:170542:50"/> truth is ſtated between two extreams, and it is good for Chriſtians to be throughly informed here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, that in the afflictions which befall them they may know how to judge of God, and alſo to deport themſelves accordingly. To judge of God, as one indeed angry and diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and whoſe anger is terrible, ſo that to a godly man, it is more dreadfull then all troubles, to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend Gods diſpleaſure to him. It is not, ſaith <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> the loſs of my childe, the troubles in my King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, that affects me ſo much, as becauſe <hi>God doth hide his face from me,</hi> Pſal.
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:170542:50"/> 51. and it muſt needs be ſo, becauſe the heart of a believer awakened for ſin, is made very tender, and ſo the frowns of God do more pierce his heart, then almoſt Hell flames do ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie the wicked: as a little offence to the eye, becauſe a tender part, is more grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous then great blows to other parts of the body. The godly therefore are not to deſpiſe the rod of God, yea, none are more to lay it to heart then they. But further, as they are to be ſenſible of his anger, ſo withal to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure themſelves that he is angry, becauſe he loveth them: that this bitter
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:170542:51"/> fruit doth come from a ſweet root: that all his exerciſes have their riſe from a Fatherly care to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they are to receive them as medicinal, not as poenal and deſtructive.</p>
                     <p>But I ſhall not inlarge further herein: let us for the more particular affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of our ſelves, who pretend to have an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in the Lord more then others, conſider the grounds why God will not let his own people,<note place="margin">Reaſons why God will pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh his own peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple for their ſins.</note> when ſinning, to go unpuniſhed; they muſt be called to a ſevere account, yea when God letteth the wicked ones of the world live in
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:170542:51"/> their eaſe, go on ſecurely in their impieties, and bleſſing themſelvs therein; at the ſame time the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for leſſer ſins ſhall have the bitter cup of affliction to drink of, ſo that by out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward events you would think the godly only were hated by God, &amp; the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked loved: And the <hi>firſt</hi> ground of Gods judging his own people, if not judging and humbling themſelves, may be from the <hi>order,</hi> and <hi>way</hi> which God hath appointed for the communicating of Chriſts benefits to us, for this is the foundation of that Antinomian errour mentioned, when they
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:170542:52"/> read ſuch places, as that Chriſts blood <hi>is made an atonement for our ſins: that the father laid our iniquities upon him: that he is made righteouſneſs to us, and that we are accepted of in Chriſt:</hi> They think this is all, and becauſe this is accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Chriſt, though we be wallowing in our luſts, they think theſe great merci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s are to be applied to us, but they are to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the other places as well of believing, of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, not that they are cauſes, or merits, or to be oppoſed to Chriſt, but they are the qualifications of ſuch ſubjects to whom Chriſt will thus reveal
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:170542:52"/> himſelf; and the Pool, as it were in moving whereof the Angel cometh down, and healeth us, ſo that its a bleſſed thing to avoid extremities in this point in our afflictions, not to be ſecurely preſuming, nor yet ſlaviſhly dejected; not to look upon a Chriſt without duties, nor yet oppoſe duties to Chriſt.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Another ground why God may even break the bones, yea the heart as it were of his own chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren when offending him, is from the many aggrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that are to be found in the ſinnes of the godly, ſo that the like cannot be found in the tranſgreſſions
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:170542:53"/> of the wicked man, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that the offences of the godly do in ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects more diſpleaſe God, then all the ſins of wicked men: As firſt, when the people of God ſin, it is againſt more experience of the ſweetneſs and comfort by grace, and alſo of the bitterneſs of ſin, which they have felt in their own ſouls; and certainly this muſt highly aggravate thy ſin, thou knoweſt what the ſongs and joys are, of an heart reconciled to the Father through Chriſt. Thou knoweſt how bitter a thing it is for God, to ſhut thee out of his doors for thy tranſgreſſions, to
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:170542:53"/> give thee childrens bread no longer, but to ſuffer thee to live upon husks: Oh what an aggravation is this to every ſin thou fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt in, to remember theſe experiences: Alas, the wicked when they ſin, they never taſted of a better life; they never found any thing ſweeter then the creature; therefore they think they do not ſin to their loſs, and ſo they have not experimentally felt the terrours of the Lord it may be upon their ſouls: hence it is no wonder if they eat poiſon for honey; but for thee who haſt been taught all theſe things up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thy ſoul, to meddle
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:170542:54"/> with ſin that coſt thee ſo dear; to deprive thy ſelf of that joy and heaven thou haſt had: Oh tremble under the approaches of any ſin to the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> Chriſt uſed this as a motive in his prayer for thoſe who crucified him, <hi>Father for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give them, for they know not what they do;</hi> but how ſhall Chriſt ſay, forgive thee, who knoweſt what thou doeſt: All the expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience God hath wrought in thee about holy things, doth ſadly aggravate thy evil ways.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. As the godly ſin againſt more experience, ſo they alſo rebell againſt more light and knowledg,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:170542:54"/> which is always highly ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravating a ſin: What made the Angels ſins to be ſo greatly diſpleaſing to God? What made <hi>Adams</hi> ſin ſo highly offenſive? amongſt other reaſons this was one. They ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned againſt a great deal of light and knowledge which God had indued them with: Now the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly man hath not onely natural light, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed light; he is ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturally illuminated, and that not only in a common way, as many Hypocrites are, but in a ſpecial and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar manner, ſuch as no reprobate can attain unto; oh then how greatly muſt
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:170542:55"/> God be offended, when thou ſhalt ſin againſt that quick, penetrating, and tender light, which ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth in thy breaſt; and therefore God will judge thee for thy he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rt-ſins, thy ſoul-ſins; the pride there, the unbelief there, becauſe thou haſt light to diſcover all theſe. Any falſe motions, any ſinfull inten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ions, any corrupt minglings of thy ſelf with the things of God, theſe God will judge, becauſe thou haſt ſpiritual light within thee, which like the Sun-beams make thee diſcover thoſe atomes, thoſe ſecret little ſins, that other vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap> u wouldſt
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:170542:55"/> never take any notice of; remember then what light thou haſt put under a buſhel, as it were, and then no wonder if God judge thee for this.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. The godly mans ſin is more hainous then the wicked mans, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of that love, that Free-grace, thoſe bowels of mercy ſhewed to him, which never were to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly men. No wonder then, if of all ſins God will not bear the abuſe of his love and his grace, eſpecially that diſcrimina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting grace; he gave his Son to thee, not to another, who if converted, might have done him more ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice:
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:170542:56"/> his Grace did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert thee, change thee when thou waſt as fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward as others, wallowing in thy luſts as others, and ſo how can God take thy rebellion againſt ſo much Free-grace; what patience is it, that Hell doth not ſwallow thee quick up: As the Apoſtle argueth comparatively the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of Chriſt, <hi>To which of the Angels ſaid he, Thou art my Son:</hi> ſo to what wicked man, to what un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>converted man, abiding in his ſins, hath God drawn nigh with that grace and favour, as he hath to thee? how unreaſonable is it to turn grace then into wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſs:
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:170542:56"/> Argue as <hi>Ezra</hi> did, <hi>cap,</hi> 9.13. <hi>Thou haſt given us ſuch a deliverance as this, and ſhould we again break thy Commandments, O Lord, thou haſt done for me more then for many thouſands, who ſit under the power of their luſts, and ſhall I deſpiſe this love of God?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="4">4. The godly mans ſin is to be aggravated, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the ſpecial pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges which God doth beſtow upon him; for he maketh him his Son, his Friend, admits him into his preſence and favour. Now thou who art at ſuch a Feaſt always, ſhouldſt never be without thy Wedding-garment: <hi>Seem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:170542:57"/> it light to you,</hi> ſaid <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid, to be Son in Law to a King:</hi> and thus, is it a ſmall matter to be taken into Gods favour, to be his adopted children; to be in communion with him; to ſtand, as it were, before him: ſurely this muſt greatly aggravate thy ſin: The more favour and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour from God, the more abominable is thy ſinful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. <hi>Michal</hi> told <hi>David</hi> falſly, <hi>Thou haſt made thy ſelf like one of the vile per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons:</hi> but it is true of thee, Is it for one accuſtomed to the Kings preſence to be tumbling in mire and dirt. Oh ſhame thy ſelf in thy humiliation for this; how
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:170542:57"/> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comely is this to a juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed perſon? how unſuitable to the ſpirit of Adoption; obſerve that paſſage, 1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 11.9. God was angry with <hi>Solomon,</hi> becauſe his <hi>heart was turned from God,</hi> which had appeared to him twice: How many times in a gracious man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner hath God appeared to thy ſoul, and wilt thou provoke him?</p>
                     <p n="5">5. The godly mans ſins are the more hainous be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe committed againſt greater obligations, and bonds to the contrary; for every duty, every ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance is a greater obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt ſin. The more thou haſt prayed againſt
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:170542:58"/> paſſions, &amp; yet paſſionate: the more thou haſt prayed againſt pride, and yet proud; and ſo of every ſin, the greater is thy ſin. God will bring thy prayers, thy duties to witneſs againſt thee, haply the wicked man never, or very ſeldom hath prayed againſt his evil ways; but in every confeſſion, in every prayer thou haſt bewailed, and reſolved againſt ſuch evils, and therefore in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, the greater aggrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſin, when commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Again the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Lords Supper that is a ſtrong &amp; mighty obligation againſt ſin. Now the godly they are
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:170542:58"/> admitted to this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, they are not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to ſtand in the Court, but they may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the Holy of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies; they are children, and this bread is to be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to them. Now if they walk in proud ſinful waies, what a witneſs wil this or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance be againſt thee; did ye receive Chriſt to ſerve the Devil? Did ye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Chriſt to vaine &amp; unbelieving thoughts. Oh know that all ſins af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter obliging Ordinances have a kind of perfidiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Covenant-break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in them, and this muſt needs aggravate.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. The ſins of Gods
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:170542:59"/> people are to be heightned in this conſideration, that they are not only tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions, but unkind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, and therefore they are ſaid not only to anger God, but to grieve him, as <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.30. <hi>Grieve not the holy Spirit of God:</hi> God complaineth of <hi>Iſrael</hi> who were his people in a peculiar manner, though all not upright in heart, <hi>that forty years long they had grieved him:</hi> and tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly what grieveth the ſpirit of God, muſt exceeding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly grieve us. Hence though the ſins of the godly can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be that ſin againſt the Holy Ghoſt, which the Scripture makes unpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pardonable,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:170542:59"/> yet becauſe the Spirit of God, is in the godly a Sanctifier, a Sealer, a Comforter, and work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth choice and glorious ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects in them; therefore they do in a more ſpecial manner grieve the Spirit of God. The Spirit of God dwels in the godly as in his Temple, and not ſo in a wicked man; now to defile this Temple, to prophane this Temple by applying thy ſelf to any evil way, how diſtaſtfull muſt it be to the Spirit of God: Oh remember, wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked mens ſins anger God, but thine do grieve him alſo; as a ſtubborn child doth not only offend his
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:170542:60"/> parents, but make them inwardly grieve alſo.</p>
                     <p n="7">7 The people of God in their ſins have this aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vating particular why God ſhould judge them rather then others, becauſe they have greater power to withſtand it, there is not that neceſſity upon them in ſinning, as is in unrege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate men: It is true, an unregenerate man cannot but ſin in all that he doth, yet this neceſſity doth not excuſe but aggravate, both becauſe it is voluntarily contracted upon himſelf, and becauſe this neceſſity is voluntary, and with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, <hi>Eo magis libera quo magis Ancilla,</hi> as <hi>Bernard:</hi>
                        <pb n="107" facs="tcp:170542:60"/> But now in a godly man, there is a ſpiritual life and power within him to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void ſin; he is not in the progreſſe of holineſſe, as in the firſt converſion, meerly paſſive, but now <hi>actì agimus,</hi> and <hi>moti mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vemus;</hi> the grace of God exciting, we have life within us to co-operate. Now then, if God hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed ſuch a life within us, it is thy greater ſin, if thou doſt not act accordingly: God hath brought thee out of thy firſt bondage, and if thou doſt yet live a ſlave, the greater is thy condemnation. It's made a diſpute, whether a godly man can avoid any more
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:170542:61"/> ſins then he doth, or do any more good then he doth: Some Orthodox men are reported by the Arminians to affirm they cannot; but no doubt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting grace takes away that ſpiritual death in ſin, and giveth principles of life, and all habits of grace infuſed, have a ſufficiency in their way to produce their acts, yet ſo as they need actual grace to excite and apply theſe to opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. A man that hath his eye healed, hath a power to ſee, yet if there be not light to actuate the <hi>medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,</hi> he cannot ſee. We need grace even after con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, to excite and
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:170542:61"/> quicken thoſe principles: But this ſheweth that a godly mans ſin is therefore to be aggravated, becauſe he hath a principle within to refuſe it.</p>
                     <p n="8">8. Hence it is, becauſe of this ſupernatural life within him, that all the ſins of a godly man have a kinde of unnaturalneſſe in them; when a wicked man ſinneth, he ſinneth of his own, it is naturall, as it is for a ſerpent to be poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonous, for a wolf to be ravening; but if a godly man ſin, it's wholly <hi>contra</hi>-natural: How cometh this figtree to bear thorns, this Vine to bear thiſtles? Hence, 1 <hi>Joh</hi> 3.9. <hi>he that
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:170542:62"/> is born of God,</hi> is ſaid, <hi>not to ſinne,</hi> yea <hi>he cannot ſinne, becauſe the ſeed abideth in him,</hi> for ſins are againſt his divine principle; it is as if iron ſhould ſwim, as if fire ſhould deſcend: <hi>How can I do this and ſin againſt God,</hi> ſaid <hi>Joſeph,</hi> Gen. 39.9.</p>
                     <p n="9">9. Therefore God doth judge his people when offending, becauſe their ſinnes do diſhonour God more; what diſorders are in an houſe redound to the Maſters reproach; from wicked men no other thing is expected, every one looketh that ſwine will wallow in the mire; but when ſheep do ſo, this
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:170542:62"/> is intollerable. This ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravation God putteth upon <hi>Davids</hi> ſinne, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.14. <hi>Becauſe by this deed, thou haſt given great occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for the enemies of God to blaſpheme.</hi> Now remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that the honour and glory of God is worth ten thouſand ſuch as thou art.</p>
                     <p n="10">10. And laſtly, The ſinnes of the godly are a ſtumbling block and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement to the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked; if they ſee thee proud, earthly, paſſionate, they think they may do ſo likewiſe. Beſides, thou doſt hereby diſcover ſome wearineſſe of God, as if to turn from him to ſinne
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:170542:63"/> were better, as if thou didſt not finde that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment and fulneſſe in the waies of God, as thou didſt hope for; ſo that ſeeing all theſe things are in the ſinnes of the godly, no wonder if the Lord do in a ſpecial manner, call them to account, &amp; make them taſte of the bitter cup he giveth them to drink.</p>
                     <p>Uſe of Exhortation, let the People of God then ſpeedily ſet upon this duty of ſelf-judging. It is a fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full thing to fall into the hands of God provoked; if thy heart be dull, hard, ſenſleſs, lay all theſe quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning aggravations of thy
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:170542:63"/> ſins to thy ſoul, and they muſt needs humble thee. The Sacrament of the Lords Supper, as from one conſideration, it requireth joy, and gladneſs of heart; ſo from another, godly ſorrow and brokenneſs of ſoul, to ſee Chriſt cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed, as it were, for thy ſins before thy eyes, and thou haſt been many times ready to crucifie him again and again: Cry out, O Lord, my heart is overwhelmed, what can I ſay, This ſin with theſe aggravations make me fear and tremble. Oh it is not in my own worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, in my own fitneſſe, I preſume to draw to this
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:170542:64"/> Ordinance, for with the Centurion, I am not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Chriſt ſhould come within my roof; and thus the leſſe thou ſpareſt and excuſeſt thy ſelf, the more welcome wilt thou be to this Table.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="115" facs="tcp:170542:64"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Of Gods puniſhing his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple for ſins againſt a <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive</hi> Inſtitution, ſuch as Sacrament-ſins.</head>
                     <epigraph>
                        <q>
                           <bibl>
                              <hi>1 COR. 11.31.</hi>
                           </bibl>
                           <p>For if we would judge our ſelves, we ſhould not be judged of the Lord.</p>
                        </q>
                     </epigraph>
                     <p>THE laſt Obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is, That <hi>God doth judge his people, not only for moral groſſe ſinnes, but Sacrament-ſins, ſinnes that are againſt a poſitive inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution.</hi> The <hi>Corinthians</hi> were guilty of many other
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:170542:65"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="115" facs="tcp:170542:65"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="116" facs="tcp:170542:66"/> ſins, ſome whereof were contrary to the moral Law, yea to the very light of nature; but the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle doth not inſtance in them as a cauſe of that publick judgement which was upon them, but he pitcheth on their prophane approachings to the Lords Supper, which is of a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive Inſtitution. The o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal of all that calamity which is come upon man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde, and that ſinne for which God was ſo provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, that all the poſterity of <hi>Adam</hi> is obnoxious to eternal wrath, God pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing no ſin in the like manner, as he did this; What was it? but a tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:170542:66"/> of a poſitive law. <hi>Uzzah</hi> was ſtricken dead, <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu</hi> conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with fire from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and all becauſe they did not keep to ſuch order, in Gods worſhip, as he had inſtituted: 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15.13. Yea <hi>Moſes</hi> but for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring Circumciſion, which was an Ordinance likewiſe of meer inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſo that it had been no duty to circumciſe, if God had not commanded it, yet he was threatned to be killed for his delay therein. The Paſchal lamb alſo, <hi>Exod.</hi> 4.24. to which the Sacrament of the Lords Supper doth an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, whoſoever did neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect,
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:170542:67"/> was <hi>to be cut off from among his people,</hi> Numb. 9.13. By theſe inſtances it doth appear how ſevere the wrath of God is againſt all ſuch as do not keep to the Ordinances of God, and that in ſuch order as he hath required, as we reade <hi>David</hi> acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15.13.</p>
                     <p>I ſhall not treat in the general about all the poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive inſtitutions of Chriſt, but limit my ſelf to this of the Lords Supper, and to ſhew you, that ſeeing God will ſo juſtly judge men for their unworthy ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches to it, it is good for us to judge our ſelves for ſuch ſins firſt, and this
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:170542:67"/> may prevent Gods judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of us; only to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the Doctrine, you muſt know that that ſpeaketh of ſins of two ſorts, moral ſins, and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive ſins; to underſtand which diſtinction, you muſt know, that this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion is according to the two kinds of Commands which God impoſeth upon his Church; there are moral commands, which command or forbid that which is either intrinſecal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly good, or evil; ſo that becauſe they are goo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> God commandeth them they are not commanded and therefore good: ſuc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> is to love God, to fear hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="120" facs="tcp:170542:68"/> and ſuch are the duties of the ſecond Table: for we regard not thoſe School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, who ſay nothing is intrinſecally good or evil, but meerly ſo from the outward Command of God, or his prohibition. Again, there are poſitive commands, and theſe have their goodneſs onely, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God commands them, in themſelves they have no intrinſecal good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, only Gods inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on makes them good; thus the ſanctification of the Lords Day is a duty by poſitive inſtitution: ſo the obſervation of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, it is a duty by Gods meer will and inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:170542:68"/> ſo that the not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing baptized, the not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving of the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per had not been any ſins, if God had not required them: only theſe poſitive Commands are again di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed into poſitive <hi>temporary,</hi> ſuch things as God hath required of h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s Church for a time on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as to be Circumciſed, to obſerve the Judaical Rites and Sacrifices: it was great ſinne to keep them up when the time of their obligation was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pired. 2. There is poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive <hi>perpetual,</hi> and that is when God hath appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſuch Ordinances to be obſerved till the coming
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:170542:69"/> of Chriſt, as the Lords day, Baptiſme, and the Lords Supper, we are to ſhew forth his death till he come, 1 <hi>Cor</hi> 11. This is called by ſome Divines Moral Poſitive, and the other Moral commands, are called Moral Natural. Now as there are two kinds of Laws, ſo there are ſuch kinds of ſins which are the tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thoſe Laws; when a man is unjuſt, unclean, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperate, then he breaks the natural Law of God; when he prophanes the Sabbath, when he co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth unprepared to a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, he breaketh the Poſitive Law; and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:170542:69"/> it might be thought theſe latter ſins are not ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry hainous, becauſe they are only <hi>mala quia prohibita</hi> evils, becauſe prohibited, Gods prohibition maketh them to be ſins. The Doctrine telleth us, that for ſuch ſins God will judge us: yea it is worth the while to take notice of that place, <hi>Levit.</hi> 17. <hi>ver.</hi> 3, 4, 5. where God ſpeaking not of a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane killing of beaſts for common food, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious, by way of Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, he enjoyneth this order, that whoſoever killeth a beaſt, thus for a Sacrifice, and bringeth it not unto the door of the
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:170542:70"/> Tabernacle, <hi>blood ſhall be imputed to that man, he hath ſhed blood.</hi> A notable place, to ſhew how hain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous a ſin it is not to keep to Gods order in his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. The very not bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it to the door of the Tabernacle maketh it as hainous a ſin as to kill a man; and indeed in ſome reſpects theſe ſins are worſe then the other, whereof this is the chief, becauſe the Lord doth by theſe Poſitive precepts de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate his ſoveraignty over us, and try our obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience; ſo that if we be negligent or omiſſive therein, we do expreſly and formally manifeſt our
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:170542:70"/> diſobedience to God, and do refuſe to own him as our Lord: Not to add that in theſe poſitive inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions, God regardeth our good; he hath appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Sabbaths and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, not for his good but for ours, not that he needeth us, but becauſe we need him; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we muſt highly ſin againſt our ſouls,<note place="margin">What particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars are to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined, &amp; inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red after with ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of the Lords Supper.</note> when God ſhall in ſuch a merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full manner tender our good, and we refuſe it.</p>
                     <p>This foundation laid, let us inquire into the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Self-judging in this particular Ordinance of the Lords Supper, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this judging as you
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:170542:71"/> heard doth imply a judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>diſcuſsion,</hi> and upon ſin diſcovered, a judgement of <hi>condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> Let us ſpeak to both, and for the judgement of <hi>Diſcuſsion:</hi> theſe things are to be done, firſt the worthy Receiver, who may receive comfortably, is to judge himſelf about the ſtate of grace, to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine himſelf, whether he be a new creature, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther God hath ever put a ſupernatural and heavenly principle in him, or no? for if he be a man in the ſtate of nature ſtill? If he have no more in him then what he came with into the world, he cannot
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:170542:71"/> put forth thoſe actual gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Faith, and ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al hunger after Chriſt, and his benefits, which make the Lords Supper to be ſpiritual meat and nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment indeed. There was once a prophane cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom crept into the Church, which was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved by a Council, That the Lords Supper ſhould no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> be given to dead men, and the elem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nts being ſymbols of nouriſhment, in the uſe whereof we a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e commanded to eat and drink, all this ſuppoſeth that while men are dead in ſins, void of ſpiritual life, they cannot ſpiritually eat and drink, nor put forth
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:170542:72"/> gracious actings in the Ordinances; for there muſt be a good root, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e the branches be good; there muſt be a good Fountain, ere the ſtreams be; and ſo a good foundation of grace and ſpiritual life within, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou art able to put forth Sacramental act ngs; only you muſt remember that the Church admits ſuch to this Table that have competent know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and are free from groſs ſins, becauſe ſhe can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not judge of the hearts of men: neither is the Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, or Regeneration of a perſon, either in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, or the Lords Supper
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:170542:72"/> a foundation of the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; for then the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter would be in perpetual doubtings to whom to give it to, or ra her con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude to give it to none, becauſe he cannot certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly judge of grace in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mans heart, but the ground of our adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is Chriſts command, with the order and way he hath preſcribed. Now the Word doth only barr ignorant and prophane, the other are admitted to come; yet they muſt know that without a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of regeneration, they cannot ſpiritually eat and drink at this Feaſt. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:170542:73"/> reſt not in mans ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation, that is but a poor reed to lean upon: you ſee the Officers let in that man to the Feaſt, and did not keep him out, who came without a wedding-garment; but the Maſter of the Feaſt, when he co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth and vieweth them, he finds him out, ſaying, <hi>Friend, how cameſt thou hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, without a wedding gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</hi> Mat. 22.12. which made him ſpeechleſs im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly; he did not plead, thy ſervants admitted me, they bid me come; ſo nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wilt thou be able to plead, who being not born again, or in a ſtate of grace, approacheſt to this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance:
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:170542:73"/> Lord I was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by the Miniſters, I gave them ſatisfaction. This is not enough, but ſearch into the bottom of thy ſoul, inquire what are the great things God hath done to thy inward man: remember it is <hi>menſa A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quilarum,</hi> not <hi>Graculorum,</hi> a Table for Eagles, not Jayes, as <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> ſaid. If a gracious heart doubt about this work of grace in himſelf; ſuch an one is to know that his duty is to come; for where there is a ſenſe of ſin, an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gering after Chriſt, a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wailing of our infirmities, theſe are incouragements for thee to come, though
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:170542:74"/> it may be thou art not aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured of thy being in the ſtate of Grace: many of Gods children would be denied this bread, if none might come, but thoſe that had aſſurance of their being in Chriſt. I have not time to inlarge on this</p>
                     <p n="2">2. We are to judge our ſelves about our preſent fitneſs, and capacity for the Lords Supper: Not only whether grace be in us for the main, but whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be actuated, and preparing the ſoul, that it is like a room ready ſwept &amp; dreſt to receive Chriſt: Every godly man is not in an immediate fitneſs to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:170542:74"/> the Lords Supper. Some of theſe <hi>Corinthians</hi> were truly godly, as was proved, yet they became guilty of unworthy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving, by their actual in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpoſition. The inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment may want tuning for preſent melody; the k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>y may be ruſty; the heart may be ſo dul, unbelieving, c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rnal, and unſavoury, that there is not a preſent tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of heart to cloſe with thoſe Ordinances as he ought to do. If thy heart be a Fountain, but ſealed up; if a Box of oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but not opened; there is a gulf be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>en Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramental benefits and thy heart. If you ask,
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:170542:75"/> what doth actual fitneſs conſiſt in: I anſwer it is in the actual exerciſe of thoſe graces, the principles whereof are in thy ſoul: It is like the wind breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon the flowers of a garden, which make them ſend forth a ſweet ſmell; its like a tool whetted, like a Spring running, like a fire kindled, many times thou haſt wood laid toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the principles of grace within thee, but there is not fire that doth kindle it; the graces to be actually put forth, are a renewed ſorrow and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der meltings of thy heart for thy former impieties; ſerious meditation about
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:170542:75"/> Chriſt his Perſon, his Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, his unſpeakable love in dying for thee, not to give over thinking about this, till thou finde it prove like coals of fire in thy boſom; Heavenly mindedneſs likewiſe lift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth up thy heart, and makes thee ſuitable to heavenly gifts; ſpiritual hungrings and longings of ſoul after the benefits re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, holy joy and glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of heart, with great thankfulneſs unto God: Oh when a ſoul is dreſſed in all theſe ornaments, <hi>the Lillies of the field, nor</hi> So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon <hi>in all his glory, is not like it:</hi> As therefore the maſter invited his gueſts,
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:170542:76"/> ſaying, <hi>Come for all things are ready,</hi> is it likewiſe true of thee concerning thy fitneſs, I come Lord, for all is ready, my ſoul is put in order, the heart is furniſhed to receive Chriſt. And if the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſoul ſay, oh this is that which troubleth me; I am ſo diſordered, my heart is untuned, this diſquiets me, that diſtracts me, my heart is in an uproar, no fitneſs is there to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Chriſt. To ſuch an humbled ſoul I ſay, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe theſe things are a burden to thee, thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſireſt theſe mountains might be levelled, and theſe valleys raiſed; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:170542:76"/> thy ſoul is in ſome preparedneſs and fitneſs, though not ſo much as thou wouldſt be: the more empty and lowly in thy own eyes, the more welcome to Chriſt: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides as theſe make thee in ſome ſort fit to come, ſo they put thee in a neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of coming. Eat of this honey, that thy eyes may be inlightned; draw nigh to this Ordinance that thou mayeſt have more of Chriſt, and his graces: the more thou keepſt from this pool, as it were, the leſs healing thou canſt expect. Among many things that may be ſaid to convince and incourage
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:170542:77"/> ſuch a tempted perſon, I would chiefly propound this, Thou art afraid to come to the Sacrament; Art thou alſo afraid to come to Chriſt? Dareſt thou not lay hold on a promiſe, what! all the while thou k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>epeſt from a Sacrament, wouldſt thou alſo keep from Chriſt, and the Promiſe? Surely thou wilt return a negative to this; but conſider, thoſe that may come to Chriſt, may come to Sacraments; thoſe that may by Faith lay hold on him, may alſo draw nigh to this Feaſt: As Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, all ye that are heavy laden, and I will eaſe you:</hi>
                        <pb n="139" facs="tcp:170542:77"/> Thus doth the Sacrament, as it were ſpeak, Come unto me ye burdened ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and Chriſt in the uſe of his means will give reſt to you; thou art greatly deceived, if thou thinkeſt thou mayeſt lay hold on a promiſe, and not come to the Sacrament at that time; for a Promiſe and a Sacrament are the ſame things; the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is nothing but a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible promiſe, appointed by God to aſſure thee of his love, and to be an help againſt thy infirmities: It is true in ſome caſes of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapſes and repentings of them, there the party though believing in
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:170542:78"/> Chriſt is yet to abſtain that he may give ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to the Church, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is not only a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of Communion with Chriſt, but alſo with one another; here he may believe, and lay hold on the Promiſe, when yet in reſpect of Chriſts order, he is to forbear the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; but this publike ſatisfaction, is not to be delayed, he is to take his firſt opportunity, and then the Church is bound <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 2.8.</note> to confirm her love to him. Therefore <hi>Calvin</hi> doth well reprove ſome ancient Canons a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Church Diſcipline of too much ſeverity, when
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:170542:78"/> perſons offending were to be kept, ſome two, ſome three years, from the Lords Supper, though they did publikly humble themſelves.</p>
                     <p>In the next place from a Judgement of diſcuſſion, we are to go to a Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>condemnation;</hi> for upon winnowing of thy ſelf, thou canſt not but finde much chaff: by ſearching into thy ſelf, much corruption will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, and when this is found out, thou art to paſs a ſentence upon it: O Lord, I judge my ſelf for this folly, this luſt, I am aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of my ſelf, I dare not in my own name draw
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:170542:79"/> nigh unto thee: eſpecially let the Communicant con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn himſelf in theſe things: firſt, all his former prophane, ignorant, and irreverent approaches to this Table. Oh let thy heart tremble, to think with what ſecurity, and joll<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ty thou didſt draw nigh to this Ordinance, being full of ignorance, not able to diſcern of the duty in hand; full of prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, coming in thy ſins, and going away in thy ſins. It is a ſpeech of <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> That a man had better never have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Sacrament in all his life, then to have taken it once unworthily:
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:170542:79"/> Therefore bewail thy ſelf, think how many times thou haſt made thy ſelf guilty of the <hi>body and blood of Chriſt:</hi> Such ſins God hath not forgotten, tho thou mayſt have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten them. Happily the <hi>Corinthians</hi> did not think that it was for this ſinne God did ſo greatly afflict them: and how little do people lay to heart their former Sacrament-ſinnes, whereas horror ſhould take hold on thee, as often as thou doeſt remember, with what boldneſs and prophaneſſe thou didſt come to theſe dreadfull myſteries. 2. Judge and condemn thy ſelf for thy
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:170542:80"/> failing in all thoſe duties thou waſt obliged too by this Ordinance. If thou receiveſt theſe Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and art as proud, as carnal, as ſenſual, there is no more quickened obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience in thee, thou doeſt not live a more heavenly and ſpiritual life after this heavenly food: Know here is alſo matter of condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation: The life of Chriſt ſhould appear in him, who hath received Chriſt; As a man coming from an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pothecaries ſhop, carrieth about him ſome of the ſweet ſmell there. The Jews would not taſte any thing after the Paſchal Lamb, that the taſte
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:170542:80"/> might be long in their mouths. If you ſee one live upon excellent fare, yet as faint, and as diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſed as before; this ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gueth ſome vitiated prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple within; were there a true principle, thou wouldſt finde this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance to be ſuch ſtrength to thy ſoul, as <hi>Elias</hi> food was to his body. But thou wilt ſay, becauſe I am conſcious to my ſelf of my ſinfull wayes, and I cannot get out of theſe ſnares, therefore I will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver come to this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance. To this I anſwer, this wil not ſerve thy turn, for then thou bringeſt thy ſelf into a perplexed neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:170542:81"/> of ſinning, if thou comeſt to a Sacrament with theſe luſts upon thee, thou eateſt thy damnation, and becauſe thou do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſt wilfully live in a ſtate un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit for a Sacrament, thou indangereſt thy damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on alſo; therefore thou haſt no way to take but to reform, to repent and to be made partaker of it. This I ſpeak to warn all ſuch as live in a wilfull incapacity and unfitneſſe for a Sacrament, they will not receive, becauſe daily fal ing into ſuch ſins; but wo unto thee that thou doeſt thus wilfully indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe thy ſelf; how doeſt thou obey that command,
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:170542:81"/> 
                        <hi>Do this in remembrance of me?</hi> How greatly doeſt thou contemn Chriſt and his benefits, with the ſeal thereof; therefore lay this to heart &amp; tremble. Thou that liveſt in a wilfull un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitneſſe to come to a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, thou art no waies fit to die, no waies fit for heaven, and dareſt thou continue in ſuch a life, when if death cometh, thou art ſure to fall into hell: Meditate on this, Am I not fit for a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, how then am I fit to die! Cannot I meet Chriſt in an Ordinance, and can I meet him as a Judge? and ſo if no fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe for a Sacrament, no
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:170542:82"/> fitneſſe for heaven: <hi>With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out are dogs;</hi> this is true, both concerning heaven, and the Church.</p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:170542:82"/>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="license">
                  <pb facs="tcp:170542:83"/>
                  <head>Dethick <hi>Maior.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>Tueſday 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
                           <hi>of</hi> May, 1656.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>IT is Ordered, that M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Anthony Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſſe</hi> be deſired from this Court to Print his late Sermon at <hi>Pauls.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Sadler.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:170542:83"/>
                  <p>A DEMONSTRATION OF THE Day of Judgment, againſt ATHEISTS &amp; HERETICKS.</p>
                  <p>For the awakening of the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly, and the Comfort of Saints, eſpecially thoſe of them that are afflicted and oppreſſed.</p>
                  <p>Preached at S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                     <hi>Pauls,</hi> May 11. 1656.</p>
                  <p>By <hi>Anthony Burgeſſe</hi> Paſtor of the Church of <hi>Sutton-Coldfield</hi> in <hi>Warwickshire.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>T. Underhill</hi> at the Anchor and Bible in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, 1657.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:170542:84"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:170542:84"/>
                  <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE Sir <hi>John Dethick</hi> Lord Maior of the City of <hi>London,</hi> AND The reſt of the Aldermen.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>RIGHT HONOURABLE,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Sermon formerly preached b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>fore you and entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with your good approbation, is now in Obedience to your Order made
<pb facs="tcp:170542:85"/> more publick; whereunto I was more willingly induced, becauſe of the ſpecial uſefulneſs of the Subject. The Doctrine of the Day of Judgement, with the practical improvement thereof, being much inſiſted upon bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h by our Saviour and the Apoſtles, yea the Duties in reference to this Day, are ſo importunately urged, as that, Whether we eat or drink, whether we walk or ſit ſtill, our thoughts and meditations ſhould be fervent and affectionate about it; and which is the more to be obſerved, this Truth is a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain from which cometh bitter and ſweet; In it is both a ſting and honey; from the ſame root ſprings the Roſe and the prickles;
<pb facs="tcp:170542:85"/> Would we raiſe up our dejected and diſconſolate hearts? the thoughts of this Day, like <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids</hi> Harp, would expell all ſuch evil apprehenſions; Would we awaken our dead and dull ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits? Would we curb and bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle our immoderate affections? the meditations upon this Day would be like a fiery Sword to keep fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m them. Hence it is that the Scripture maketh this two-fola Uſe thereof, for Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort (to the Godly, I mean) Therefore <hi>(Luk. 21.28.)</hi> they are commanded upon the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of that Day, <hi>To lift up their heads, for their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption draweth near.</hi> It is a Day of Redemption to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e
<pb facs="tcp:170542:86"/> who art kept a priſoner in this <hi>Aegypt</hi> of the world; A mighty Deliverance will then be wrought for thee from ſinne and miſery; How bleſſed then and comfortable must the thoughts of this time be to thee? <hi>Luthers</hi> expreſsion was <hi>(Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon. de Signis prae. extr. Jud.) That he had rather never have been born, than not to be in hope of this Day.</hi> Hence it is that God exerciſeth his children in this Wilderneſs, that <hi>Canaan</hi> their rest in Heaven may be more deſired. <hi>Luther (ibidem)</hi> ſaith of himſelf, <hi>That once he was very an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry, and could not endure the matter of the Lords Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,
<pb facs="tcp:170542:86"/> wherein Chriſts King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom is prayed for, but after that God had toſſed him up and down with the waves and tempeſts that he met with in this world, then no Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion could be more welcome to him.</hi> He that doth not look for, and haſten Chriſts com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, is not yet weaned enough from the world, his corrupt heart is not burden enough to him. The things of this world have too much interest in his ſoul, and therefore with the children of <hi>Reuben</hi> they had rather take up their habitation on this ſide <hi>Canaan,</hi> becauſe the Land was fruitfull and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantagious: But where the
<pb facs="tcp:170542:87"/> heart is raiſed up to a ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al frame, there their hopes, deſires, and ardent affections are breaking and longing for his coming, even as <hi>Siſera</hi> his mother, <hi>Judg. 5.28.</hi> looked out at the window, expecting his triumphing return, and crying, <hi>Why is his Chariot ſo long in coming? Why tarry the wheels of his Chariot?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſecond Uſe, which is of <hi>Terrour,</hi> and thereby to keep back from ſinne, to preſerve in a conſtant watching and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, which the Scripture like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe frequently commendeth, is diligently to be heeded by eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one, eſpecially <hi>(Right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable and Right Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull)</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:170542:87"/> by you who are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to the Publick Government of that famous City, the medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation on that Day ſhould be as powerfull to awaken your ſouls for Zeal to the glory of God, and righteouſneſs in all your adminiſtrations; As the ſound of the Trumpet, and the voice of the Archangel will be effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual to raiſe your bodies. And the rather attend hereunto, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that Day among other ends is eſpecially <hi>Judicare non judicata, &amp; malè judicata,</hi> The ſinnes not judged and not puniſhed, and the things falſly and unrighteouſly judged; God will at that Day have a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>view of them, ſo that the
<pb facs="tcp:170542:88"/> crooked things which are in this world will then be made ſtraight. At that Day, rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, honours, and the pomp of the world will be in no requeſt, but an interest in Chriſt, to have him our Mediatour and Friend, who is the Judge, will be the only happineſs, of which the Lord grant you to be parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, ſo as to finde mercy in that Day, is the prayer of</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your humble Servant in the work of the Miniſtry <hi>ANTHONY BURGESSE.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170542:88"/>
                  <head>A DEMONSTRATION of the Day of Judgment.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>ACTS 17.31.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>Becauſe he hath appointed a day in which he will judge the world in righteouſneſs by that man whom he hath or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat hath <hi>Athens</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to do with each other? What the
<pb facs="tcp:170542:89"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170542:89"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="2" facs="tcp:170542:90"/> 
                     <hi>Gentiles</hi> Academy, and the Chriſtian Church? ſaid <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian,</hi> ſpeaking of Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence concerning this paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of <hi>Pauls</hi> being at <hi>Athens;</hi> yet here we ſee him like a little <hi>David</hi> going in the name of the Lord with a few Stones from the brook, ſome Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments from the Scripture, againſt the great <hi>Goliahs</hi> of the world: And in this Hiſtorical Narration we may ſee <hi>Paul</hi> performing a double ſervice for God, as a Diſputant, and as an Oratour; As a Diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant with the many Sects of Philoſophers then reigning in <hi>Athens,</hi> eſpecially the <hi>Epicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reans,</hi> (whoſe opinions were
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:170542:90"/> called <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, being ſuitable baits to draw out the fleſh of man) and the <hi>Stoicks.</hi> Now though both theſe were extremely contrary, yet they agreed in oppoſing of <hi>Paul,</hi> and therefore called him for his Doctrine <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, a tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fling babbler, a word much vext by Criticks; and <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin</hi> ſaith, though of deriders <hi>Paul</hi> was called, <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>minator ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borum,</hi> yet of believers he may in a good ſenſe be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged to be ſo, becauſe of the good ſeed of the Word he did abundantly ſow, from which came a great crop.</p>
                  <p>But <hi>Paul</hi> doth not only en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:170542:91"/> with Philoſophers, he is brought to <hi>Areopagus,</hi> that famous place with Heathen Writers, where he makes a grave and admirable Oration, of which my Text is part. In which we may conſider the place where, the general is <hi>Athens,</hi> the bright luminary of the world for Learning, <hi>Linguata Civitas,</hi> as <hi>Tertullian</hi> calleth it, a City of the tongue, whoſe manners are ſaid to be exerciſed in enquiring after, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, a diſe3ſe many times in the Chriſtian Church, many being weary of ſolid and known Doctrines, deſiring of that which is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard and unknown, and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:170542:91"/> to be in the <hi>Terrâ incogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tâ,</hi> or uninhabitable part of Divinity: The proper place is <hi>Areopagus, Mars</hi>-hill, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led ſo, either becauſe <hi>Mars</hi> was here accuſed for his impiety, or elſe becauſe it was a ſevere Court of Juſtice againſt all unjuſt, violent, murderous actions. This <hi>Areopagite</hi> Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicature is famous, they did excel ſo much in Authority, that Kings laid down their Crowns when they came to ſit with them; they were of ſuch integrity that they kept their Court, and gave Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the night, and in the dark, that they might not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the perſons who did
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:170542:92"/> ſpeak, leſt they ſhould be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved thereby, they only did hear what was ſaid; here it was that the pleader muſt not uſe any <hi>Proemium,</hi> nor make any rhetorical expreſſion to move the affections; Hence it was that they did bear as much reverence to the Senten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Decrees promulged there, as they did to their ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Oracles, and here <hi>Paul</hi> is placed. <hi>Grotius</hi> thinks not, as to the Court there, in a ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridical manner, but others judge contrary; however <hi>Paul</hi> is undaunted, and being an earthly Angel, as <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> calleth him, feareth not the power of man.</p>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:170542:92"/>
                  <p>In his Oration we may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the crime he chargeth upon them, and that is Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition in the univerſal extent of it in al things <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, where <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> doth <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dundant, as ſome think, or elſe it is emphatical, for there is <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>veritatis,</hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>ſimilitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinis,</hi> which may explain that place againſt the <hi>Socinians, Joh.</hi> 1.14.</p>
                  <p>Some learned men think the word Superſtition is uſed in an indifferent and middle ſenſe, as the word Hereſie is ſometimes, yea ſome ſay <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks here in their commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, and therefore uſeth the comparative more ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:170542:93"/> or religious, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed they were exceſſively devout in their Religion, as among other things is plain concerning <hi>Anaxagoras,</hi> whom they adjudged to death, becauſe he held the Sunne, which they worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped as god, to be but <hi>Saxum ignitum</hi> a white fiery ſtone; but this is not probable, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe afterwards he calleth it an ignorant Worſhip, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the word is not here uſed in an indifferent ſenſe, much leſs a laudable one. The in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance by which he proveth their ſuperſtition, is an Altar with this Inſcription <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, as the <hi>Romans</hi> had their
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:170542:93"/> 
                     <hi>Incerti Dij,</hi> and therefore ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificed <hi>ſine Deo, fine Dea;</hi> ſo the <hi>Grecians</hi> not knowing which was according to their blinde Idolatry <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, the proper god, to repel ſuch an evil, made theſe Inſcription, <hi>To the Unknown God;</hi> The Apoſtle to inform them here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in inſtructs them both about the true God, who he is, and the true manner of Worſhip; After which he comes to the Exhortatory part of his Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which is grounded upon Gods diſpenſation to thoſe times of <hi>Ignorance he winked at</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>; here may be much diſpute about the ſalvation of <hi>Heathens,</hi> becauſe it is ſaid,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:170542:94"/> 
                     <hi>God winked at it,</hi> and ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed generally it is interpret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but the <hi>Septuagint</hi> uſe the word for to <hi>deſpiſe and be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry,</hi> Deut. 3.26. Pſal. 78. and ſo <hi>to puniſh,</hi> and in this ſenſe it ſeems to be uſed here. Thoſe <hi>times of ignorance</hi> in Idolatry God was <hi>angry with,</hi> puniſhing of them with tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral and ſpiritual judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but now the grace of the Goſpel, and <hi>the love of God hath appeared in command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing every one to repent:</hi> And my Text is the reaſon and forcible ground of repentance, <hi>Becauſe he hath appointed a day.</hi> And</p>
                  <p>In the words, Conſider,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:170542:94"/> The Authour or Effici<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nt Cauſe, <hi>God hath appointed a day;</hi> God that is Juſt, Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcient, Omnipotent, <hi>He hath appointed a day,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, he hath ſetled it ſo that there is no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealing of it, there cannot be any reverſing of it, though ungodly men would give worlds to have it cancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. There is the Matter it ſelf <hi>[A Day]</hi> Here is much diſpute about the length; Some ſay this Day is a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand years, wherein God will be judging of the world; It is certain, that there will be no proper Natural, or Artificial Day, as we account; but ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:170542:95"/> the Scripture hath not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined the duration, who can define it?</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The End why ſuch a Day is appointed, and that is <hi>to judge;</hi> Now God ſeemeth to take no notice of the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieties and ungodlineſs of wicked men, for they at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent eat, drink, and rejoyce in their iniquities, but there is a <hi>Day wherein God will judge the world.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. The Object, <hi>The World;</hi> None is exempted, great as well as ſmall, rich as well as poor, the mighty as well as the weak, whoſoever is of the world ſhall be judged, the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as well as the wicked; But
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:170542:95"/> differently, The godly with a judgement of Diſcuſſion and Approbation, the wicked with a judgement of Diſcuſſion and Condemnation.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. The Manner how, <hi>in righteouſneſs;</hi> Righteouſneſs is here put partly for <hi>Truth,</hi> and partly for <hi>Juſtice,</hi> whereby he hateth ſinne, and will puniſh it: ſo that the opinion of the <hi>Socinians,</hi> which ſaith, there is no ſuch thing as vindicative Juſtice, eſſentially appertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto God, as it maketh Chriſt Satisfaction needleſs, ſo it openeth a wide door to all impieties.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, There is the Judge, <hi>By whom,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, an <hi>Hebraiſm</hi>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:170542:96"/> for <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> for <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> a <hi>Greciſm;</hi> Now in that Chriſt is called here a man and a Judge only appointed, a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted Judge, Hence thoſe blaſphemous <hi>Socinians</hi> deny the Eſſential Deity of Chriſt, and make him only a conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted God, but therefore is he called a man here, not exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively to God, but becauſe he ſhall judge the world in an external and viſible manner, which cannot be done by him, as God, for ſo he is inviſible; and whereas he is ſaid to be appointed a Judge, and this Judiciary Power is given him, you muſt know that many things are ſaid to be given un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:170542:96"/> Chriſt as Mediatour, which doth not diminiſh his Deity, but neceſſarily preſuppoſe it, as to be made a Judge of the whole world; None can be ſo but he who is God as well as man, for he muſt be Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcient and Omnipotent, who is this Judge, whether indeed he be a Judge in both Natures, as well in the Divine as Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane; As alſo how the Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature of Chriſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to know all the ſecret things of mans heart, is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted between us and the <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therans,</hi> but I wave it; only you muſt know, Chriſt is not an inferiour or delegate Judge, but ſupream and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:170542:97"/> chief, being God as well as man.</p>
                  <p>The Text being thus divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and opened, this Doctrine or Corollary naturally floweth from it, <hi>viZ.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That God hath appointed a Day to judge all mankinde by Christ.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This truth is an Article of Faith, and having ſuch pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfull influence upon our lives, it is good to poſſeſs our mindes with the truth of it, and our hearts with the terrour of it, for both corrupt mindes and prophane hearts have with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood this main Fundamental point: As <hi>the fool hath ſaid in his heart</hi> (by wiſh and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection)
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:170542:97"/> 
                     <hi>that there is no God:</hi> So they ſay in their hearts, there is no Day of Judgement; And as that King of <hi>France</hi> ſtrictly forbad any ſo much as to mention death in his hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, he did ſo abhorre the thoughts of it; ſo do many about the name of this Day. The Devil cannot hurry men into hell, as he did the Swine into the Sea, untill the thoughts of this Day are wholly obliturated; Therefore before Chriſts time, and ſince, there have been Doctrinal and Practical oppoſers of it; Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrinal, ſo the <hi>Sadduces,</hi> who denied the Reſurrection and Immortality of the ſoul, were
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:170542:98"/> neceſſitated alſo to deny the Day of Judgement: And as <hi>Joſephus</hi> obſerves, The <hi>Sad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces,</hi> though they were not ſo many as the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> nor ſo reputed of for Religion, yet they were the moſt potent, the greateſt in wealth and honour; So that the denial of a Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, and the Day of Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was very ſuitable to their intereſt. After Chriſts time, though this Article be ſo plainly affirmed in the New Teſtament, that no words can ſpeak it more clearly, yet there is a large Catalogue gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by learned men of blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous and damnable He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks, who do deny it; and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:170542:98"/> the <hi>Socinians</hi> in that they hold eternal torment to be the anni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hilation of the whole man, do in effect alſo renounce this ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Truth. And as for Practical Oppoſers of it, the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> doth ſignally decipher ſome even in his dayes, <hi>that were but ſcoffers</hi> and <hi>deriders</hi> at that truth which ſhould have ſtruck them into fear and tremblihg, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.3, 4. <hi>There ſhall in the laſt dayes come ſcoffers, ſaying, Where is the promiſe of his coming?</hi> No doubt all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane, ſecure and atheiſtical ſinners, who ſay, <hi>Let us eat and drink, and to morrow ſhall be as this day,</hi> though they
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:170542:99"/> do not expreſly, yet do really deny this Day, or put it farre from them. It is therefore Gods great mercy, that whereas ſome main points in Divinity are not directly in Scripture, but by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, though the ſenſe and matter be in Scripture, yet not the words; But for this Article, we have in Scripture both the truth and the words; For if there had been any evaſion, the corrupt heart of man would have ſought out plauſible inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to have denied it.</p>
                  <p>This truth is clearly aſſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed both in the Old and New Teſtament, ſo that the Scribe
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:170542:99"/> of the Kingdom of Heaven, may bring out of his Treaſure old and new; and this is the more remarkable to have it in the Old, where the truths of Heaven and Hell are more ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurely delivered; Yea the <hi>Socinians</hi> look upon the <hi>Jews</hi> under that Legal Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but as ſo many Swine, deſiring husks only, and not knowing of the Manna of the Goſpel.</p>
                  <p>That this Doctrine was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved of old, yea preſently after the fall, appeareth by what <hi>Jude</hi> relateth in his Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>verſ.</hi> 14. <hi>Enoch the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth from Adam propheſied, ſaying, Behold the Lord com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:170542:100"/> with ten thouſands of his Saints to render vengeance;</hi> And whether this was a reall or verbal Prophecy is diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; if verbal, where is that Prophecy? if it be loſt, May any part of the Canonical Scripture be loſt? And how did <hi>Jude</hi> come to know this was in <hi>Enoch</hi>'s Prophecy? Theſe are Diſputes which the practical matter I intend will not ſuffer me to treat of: Here we have a plain Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and that almoſt from the beginning, <hi>That the Lord will come with ten thouſand of his Saints to execute Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That it is a Doctrine of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:170542:100"/> great Antiquity, <hi>Solomon</hi> like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the wiſeſt of men, even in that Book, where to out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward appearance, we would think too much liberty given to carnal opinions, therefore ſome Expoſitors make him oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en ſpeak in the perſon of a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane Epicure, and ſenſual man, he giveth a two-fold te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony to this truth.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 11.9, 12, 14. <hi>God will bring every work into Judgement;</hi> And this is brought as a bridle to impiety, and a ſpur to all godlineſs.</p>
                  <p>The laſt Text I ſhall pitch on, is that famous Text, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.9, 10, 13-26. ſo much agitated in the Chiliaſtical
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:170542:101"/> Controverſie; From hence, ſaith M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Mede,</hi> the <hi>Jews</hi> took the name of the Day of Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and Chriſt uſed the expreſſion as a known thing, even as the title of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Heaven was a Jewiſh phraſe. It is true, ſome learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and pious men comparing this with <hi>Revel.</hi> 20. do im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove it not only for a Day of Judgement, but that it ſhall continue a thouſand years, wherein the Martyrs, as ſome; or all the godly, as others, ſhall be raiſed and reign in glory in the Earth a thouſand years, after which time the wicked alſo ſhall riſe to be judged, and this
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:170542:101"/> they call the firſt Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
                  <p>But as in the Doctrine of the Trinity, and Chriſts In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnation, we muſt diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh between Fundamental Truths, and Problematical; ſo in this Article the Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental is, That there ſhall be a Day of Judgement; The Problematical are ſuch which Learned and pious men may diſpute and differ in, without breach of Charity, Although for this opinion of a thouſand years, I can ſooner admire it for the wonderfull things aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted by it, than approve of it.</p>
                  <p>I come to the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:170542:102"/> And here it would be uſeleſs to accumulate many places, only two or three Texts ſhall be mentioned, that ſo our hearts may be as ſenſibly awed with it, as if with <hi>Hierom</hi> we did alwayes hear that noiſe in our ears, <hi>Ariſe ye dead and come to Judgement,</hi> Matth. 25.31. We have there a lively De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of the Day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, with the form of Chriſts judicial proceſs, as alſo the event of it, which is to divide between Goats and Sheep, the one adjudged to eternal puniſhment, the other received into eternal life; Let Faith realize this Text upon
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:170542:102"/> thy ſoul, ſet thy ſelf at Gods Barre, think as God called to <hi>Adam, Adam, Where art thou?</hi> and he was filled with ſo much fear that he hid him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; Thus God is calling, thou ſuch a ſinner, ſuch an unjuſt prophane wretch, where art thou? To what mountains and hils wilt thou call to be covered from the ſight of this Judge?</p>
                  <p>A ſecond Text is, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.7, 8, 9. there is the antecedent to this Day, All the world ſhall be on fire like a <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens and the Earth ſhall paſs away like a noiſe: As before an houſe falleth this beam
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:170542:103"/> crackleth, and that pillar ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth a noiſe: Thus it will be in the end of the world; I do not diſpute, Whether it will be an eſſential abolition, or a qualitative one, but this will be ſuch a terrible change and alteration, that the Apoſtle ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth this uſe, <hi>verſ.</hi> 11. <hi>Seeing all theſe things ſhall be diſsolv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, What manner of perſons ought we to be,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> not <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> to admiration: How is it poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to believe ſuch a day as this, and live in ungodlineſs? Thou prophane and unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous man, either thou art an Atheiſt, and doſt not believe any ſuch thing, and if ſo, What doſt thou in the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:170542:103"/> Church of God? Or if thou believeſt this day, thou art a fool and mad man, that fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt thy ſelf for deſtruction againſt that Day: Have men faith, reaſon, conſcience, whoſe thoughts are not more conſtant about it? 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4.16. There is Chriſts coming alſo deſcribed with a <hi>ſhout, the voice of the Archangel, and a trump of God;</hi> We will not diſpute the Explication of thoſe things, this is to ſhew that Chriſt will come with all the Majeſty, terrour and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry that poſſibly can be imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; and that this is certainly ſo, conſider <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.27. <hi>It is appointed for man once to die,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:170542:104"/> and after death comes Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> It is appointed, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, treaſured up in Gods Decrees, and therefore it is as ſure as death; ſo that thou maiſt no more queſtion ſuch a day then that thou ſhalt die. Beſides Scripture, let us conſider from rational demonſtrations of it. And</p>
                  <p>Firſt, It muſt be ſo from the verity and Truth of God. God you ſee hath foretold in ſo many places of ſuch a day, ſo that although it may ſeem impoſſible and incredible to men, yet Gods word will ſtand when Heaven and Earth ſhall paſſe away. Now con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider with thy ſelf, whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:170542:104"/> the Scripture hath fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told we ſee it comes to paſs in it's time; Chriſt did come in the fleſh according to the Prophecies, which went be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; The world was drowned, as <hi>Noah</hi> propheſied, <hi>while they were eating and drinking;</hi> Now ſhall all things come to paſs but this? Set Scripture, the Word of God againſt thy carnal reaſonings, and ſay, <hi>Every thing will prove a lie, but Gods word,</hi> thou wilt finde thy luſts, thy ſins, the Devil to be a liar to thee, only Gods Word will be faithfull and true.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, The righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God his puniſhing Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:170542:105"/> doth require it, therefore it is called <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>the day of Gods righteous Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and in the Text, <hi>He ſhall judge the world in righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi> The <hi>Socinians</hi> (as you heard) who deny any eſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Juſtice in God, whereby he is enclined to puniſh ſinne, as they take away the Satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Chriſt thereby, ſo alſo they weaken the neceſſity of ſuch a Day of Judgement, wherein the holy Majeſty of God will be avenged upon all the ungodly. Should ſinne ever go unpuniſhed, this would ſeem as if God were not a God hating iniquity; the Juſtice of God calleth for ſuch a day.</p>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:170542:105"/>
                  <p>Thirdly, The goodneſs and mercy of God likewiſe requireth ſuch a Day; <hi>For if the godly had only hope in this life they were more fooliſh and miſerable than any;</hi> They on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly were wiſe, who ſay, <hi>Let us eat and drink for to morrow we ſhall die.</hi> A man would keep a good conſcience in vain, and fooliſhly abſtain from the exceſſive riot of the world, eſpecially the Martyrs would be the greateſt fools of all; let them put off the crown of Glory, if this day be not; If there be no D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y of Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, they were impriſoned in vain, and died in vain; but it is called a <hi>Day of Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi>
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:170542:106"/> and the godly are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to <hi>lift up their heads with joy;</hi> then their Summer cometh, they are to look for and haſten it, for here they are ſighing, groaning, here alſo they are conflicting with proud, earthly, vain hearts, but this day wilt put a period to all, there will be no fin or ſorrow any more.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, The providence of God, as it diſpoſeth things in this life, doth plainly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare a Day of Judgement; For here in this world <hi>Solomon</hi> obſerves, <hi>All things fall alike to all, to him who feareth God, and him who feareth him not;</hi> The proſperity of the wicked,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:170542:106"/> and the adverſity of the godly hath been ſuch a perplexing ſubject to the wiſeſt of the godly Heathens, <hi>Seneca</hi> and <hi>Plutarch,</hi> that they have ſpent many thoughts about it, yea this Providence of God was ſuch a riddle to <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remiah,</hi> that without much prayer and recourſe to God, they were not able to anſwer it. Now to this Objection, which hath ſtagger'd ſo many, there is no ſuch ſatisfying and compleat anſwer, as that there is a Day of Judgement, when God will ſet every thing in its proper place, when all the world ſhall diſcern between him who is righteous, and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:170542:107"/> him that is not; therefore ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence all ſuch murmurings and diſputes with expectation of that Day, you ſhould not judge too ſoon before the laſt act be paſt; and as in the Word of God a man would make blaſphemy, if he ſhould make a period at a comma or a colon, as in this place, <hi>Thou art not a God that loveſt ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity,</hi> if he ſhould ſtop at that, <hi>Thou art not a God,</hi> and goe no farther, this would be bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſphemy: So it would be high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly derogatory to the Juſtice, Wiſdom and honour of God, if thou ſhouldſt conclude what is juſt, and what is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt, compleatly and finally
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:170542:107"/> by paſſages in this world, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the day of conſummati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all things is not yet come.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, That there is ſuch a Day, appeareth by the very implanted principles in a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral conſcience; For why is it that a man dying, whoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience is not benummed in that hour, terrours and agonies ſhould ſurprize him? And why then, and it may be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver before ſhould horrour and trouble take hold of him? <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimula vagula quae nunc abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis in loca,</hi> Oh wretched ſoul, Whither art thou now going? What will become of thee? Live I cannot, Die I dare not;
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:170542:108"/> Why, I ſay, ſhould ſuch an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh of ſpirit fall upon a man going out of the world, if not for ſome implanted ſenſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout a future judgement? For we might think a man though never ſo vile, might then be leaſt troubled about his ſinnes, he then feareth no Law to convince him, no Judge to condemn him, no Neighbours to ſhame him, and yet for all this he trembleth and qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth in his ſoul, not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what to do. To bring this coal yet neerer into your boſoms to inflame there, I ſhall lay down ſome Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions about the day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. As</p>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:170542:108"/>
                  <p>Firſt, It will be the laſt day of Gods great working, as to the world, God will then make to ceaſe all that kinde of government in Church and State, as is now upon the earth adminiſtred; So that it being the laſt Day of Gods Power, Majeſty, Glory, in reference to mankinde, we muſt think that that day will be anſwerable to the greatneſs of the Judge, hence he is to come in the Clouds, as ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny bright Thrones of Glory, with an innumerable company of Angels: So that God, though he hath in many par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular and publick judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſhewed forth his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:170542:109"/> power, yet never like what will be at that Day; it is the laſt day, and all dayes em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pty into it; All our words, works and thoughts have an influence into that Day, ſo that in this ſenſe we may ſay, Every thought is Eternal, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very word is Eternal, every action is Eternal, theſe die not, but all live till the Day of Judgement; What holy care and diligence ſhould this put us upon in all things? It is ſaid of <hi>Apelles,</hi> that being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, why he was ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberate and curious in draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his pictures? anſwered, he did <hi>pingere aeternitati,</hi> he painted for Eternity, not the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:170542:109"/> preſent Age only, but many ſucceſſive Ages were to judge of his work: Thus all we do, we do to Eternity, at the Day of Judgement it will be all revived: thy ſinnes die not, thy good works die not, all theſe wil then be mentioned, as if done but to day; So that this is the laſt Day, wherin all days with the works therein are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volved, after this there is no more day of grace, no more Manna will fall, no Angel will deſcend into the pool; the world is then as to this kind of adminiſtration put to an end.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, As it is the laſt Day, ſo it is a terrible and dreadfull Day, the very name
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:170542:110"/> a day of Judgment, Dooms day is enough to ſtrike terrour into us. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. It is called <hi>the day of wrath, and the revelation of the righteous Judgment of God;</hi> it is terrible in the antecedent ſigns as <hi>Matth.</hi> 24. in the conco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitant, in the nature of it, all the ſecret and evil wayes of mankinde being to be judged, in the conſequent of it, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears in that ſentence, <hi>Depart ye curſed;</hi> and it muſt needs be terrible, becauſe the Judge will then ſet himſelf to appear terribly, ſo that all the terrour and dread God can put forth, will then be manifeſted; and this maketh the Scripture re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent it by all thoſe expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:170542:110"/> which may make it for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midable; And certainly, if the report of it be ſo dreadful, what will the Day it ſelf be? Then every wicked man will ſay, as the Queen of <hi>Sheba,</hi> concerning <hi>Solomon, That ſhe had heard was nothing to what ſhe did ſee;</hi> Hence alſo the wicked are brought in, gnaſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their teeth, and crying to mountains and to hils for to cover them; This will be the more terrible, not onely becauſe all external objects will be horrid and dolefull ſights, <hi>viZ.</hi> The world on fire, the wicked roaring and yelling, but becauſe God will then fill the hearts of men
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:170542:111"/> with terrour and trembling, their ſpirits will be prepared for it; What is the reaſon that now the thought of this Day doth not aſtoniſh thee, doth not make thee a <hi>Magor-miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſabib,</hi> fear and terrour round about? but becauſe thy heart is a ſtone, God doth not make it ſenſible and apprehenſive; but at that Day, as the ſpirits of the juſt ſhall be perfected and raiſed up to love God, and to delight in him more then ever: So the ſpirits of wicked men will be more enlarged to receive horrour, they will be made more capacious of ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour than now they are; though now under theſe
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:170542:111"/> truths, thou art like <hi>Jobs Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viathan,</hi> that doſt laugh at the ſpear, and we ſeem but as bablers, telling you the Poets f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bles of the <hi>Stygian lake,</hi> and the helliſh furies, yet when this Day cometh indeed, mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and horrour will fill thy heart whether it will or no; Above is horrour, if thou lookeſt to Chriſt the Judge; About thee is terrour, the Devils ready to take thee to an eternal priſon; Below is hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, hell opening its mouth to ſwallow thee up in thoſe flames; and within thee is the greateſt horrour, there is the gnawing worm which never dieth; Think then of ſinne,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:170542:112"/> look upon thy luſts, as thou wouldſt then at that Day; Would I do as I do, if I were at Gods Tribunal, if I were arraigned at that dreadful Day?</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, It is a wonderfull Day, a Day wherein there are nothing but miracles upon mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, and wonders upon wonders: Inſomuch that we need a divine faith in this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle, as well as in any other, <hi>Prorſus incredibile quia impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibile,</hi> as <hi>Tertullian</hi> of Chriſts Incarnation; The Scripture tels us, ſuch a Day will be, and we muſt not be curious <hi>Quomodiſts,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Quomodo,</hi> How can it be? There is a
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:170542:112"/> 
                     <hi>Quomodo eſsentiale,</hi> and a <hi>Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modo accidentale</hi> in every main point of Divinity; The eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial <hi>Quomodo</hi> we are to enquire after, that is, Whether the thing be or no? But for the accidental it is good to ſatisfie our ſelves with that of <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory,</hi> He that in Gods doings doth not <hi>invenire rationem fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cti,</hi> may eaſily <hi>in ſeipſo inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nire rationem cur non inveniat;</hi> yet let us inſtance in ſome of thoſe miracles at that wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Day; What a wonder is it that all the perſons, who e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver were in the world, though their bodies have conſumed ſo many wayes, yea eaten it may be by other creatures, yea it
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:170542:113"/> may be by ſome <hi>Cannibals</hi> or ſavage men, yet all thoſe very bodies riſe again, and the ſame individual perſons appear be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God? <hi>This corruptible,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paul) cutem tangens,</hi> as <hi>Tertullian.</hi> This is ſo great a miracle, that the Philoſophers derided it. Another wonder is, that all the millions and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite millions of perſons ſhould be gathered into one place; As for thoſe who ſay, it will be the valley of <hi>Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaphat,</hi> with their conceits thereupon, we leave it as a curioſity. This is wonderful, that all the perſons which ever lived in all Ages (Infants not excepted, for they muſt riſe
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:170542:113"/> up to be judged) ſhould all be convened together. A third wonder is, Chriſts audible voice to ſpeak in the ears of all the world, and in ſuch a bodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly manner to pronounce his Sentence of condemnation: Some indeed have thought there will be no audible pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciation by Chriſt, but that ſhall only be mental in every mans conſcience; but we muſt not depart from the Letter of the Scripture, unleſs neceſſity compel; As for the Diſpute about the Trump, whether it be a material one, as alſo the fire, yea and hell it ſelf be a place and material, theſe are here impertinent. Laſtly, what
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:170542:114"/> a wonder is this, that upon the pronunciation of departing to hell, every one ſhall obey, the conſcience of every one ſhall yeeld to it, that they cannot withſtand the ſentence of God? you would think they would rather be torn in pieces, then depart into fire, but they muſt do it.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, It is an uncertain Day in reſpect of our know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, though certain that it ſhall be; that this Day and hour cannot be known by any man, is plain from what our Saviour ſpeaks, who ſaith, <hi>Neither men, nor Angels, nor the Son of man, as man, knoweth it:</hi> Therefore the opinion of ſome is very ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:170542:114"/> who have concluded the time of this Day may be known, but the event hath to ſome proved their opinion a lie. In the Apoſtles dayes, ſome pretended Revelations from the Spirit about the Day, and in theſe later dayes, ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded perſons have in ſome pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces run up and down, making an horrid and dolefull noiſe, crying out, <hi>Repent, Repent, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Day of Judgement is come;</hi> Yea, ſome vain and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous Aſtrologers, who uſe to foretell other mens conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and yet never know what ſhall befall themſelves, as they have thoughts that <hi>Noah</hi>'s floud, and Chriſts birth might
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:170542:115"/> have been foretold by the Stars, Nay ſome have bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſphemouſly ſaid, That Chriſt wrought ſuch miracles, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was born under ſuch a Conſtellation: So theſe do conclude, that by the Stars we may know the time of the Day of Judgement; but the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture compareth it to a <hi>Thief coming in the night,</hi> and to a <hi>ſnare for the bird,</hi> it will come upon all <hi>unexpected and unlook<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for.</hi> It is true, many ſober Divines, though they ſay the time cannot exactly be deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, yet think it is not farre off, yea from this year and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, they look for mighty alterations in the world; ſo that
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:170542:115"/> they think it not improbable, that ſome now living may not die till theſe things be. But theſe ſeem only conjectures, Let us content our ſelves with this, that it is certain, and the time uncertain, that we ſhould not have oyl to provide for, when the Bridegroom is come, that we ſhould not cry out with him, <hi>Inducias uſque ad mane,</hi> Let me alone longer, I am not yet ready for that Day.</p>
                  <p>The Doctrinals thus diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patcht, let us proceed to the practicals; for if any Article in Religion hath that bleſſing upon it, <hi>Increaſe and multiply,</hi> I know none more uſefull and
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:170542:116"/> profitable then this. And</p>
                  <p>The firſt Uſe ſhall be of <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation</hi> in general to all. God commandeth every one to <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, in that he hath appointed a Day wherein he will judge the world.</hi> I ſhall not encounter with thoſe Heterodox opinio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts, who think it is too legal, and not becoming a Goſpel-Miniſtry to preach of this dreadfull ſubject, as if theſe Arguments did not belong to an Evangelical ſpirit, for Chriſt was then a Legal preacher, and <hi>Paul,</hi> who doth ſo often treat on this ſubject. Indeed we may ſee the goodneſs and love of God in this, that he doth threaten with Hell, with the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:170542:116"/> Day of Judgement; For why doth he thus foretell about it, but to have thee provide for it? Once he ſet a flaming Sword in anger to keep <hi>Adam</hi> out of Paradiſe, but now he lifts up this fiery Sword in mercy to keep thee out of hell, he threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens thee with the Day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that it may be a Day of Redemption to thee; How inexcuſable then art thou (oh ſinful man) who believeſt ſuch a Day, and yet doſt not repent before it be too late? What pleaſure or ſweetneſs wilt thou then finde in thy luſts, when thou ſhalt ſay with <hi>Jonathan, I have tasted a little honey, and I must die,</hi> I have had a little
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:170542:117"/> pleaſure of ſin, and now I muſt for ever be damned? <hi>Nebuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neZZar</hi> erected a golden Image with this terrible Comminati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>That whoſoever would not fall down and worſhip it, ſhould be caſt into the fiery furnace.</hi> Now this was ſo terrible to every one, that unleſs it were three or four, there were none that did reſiſt, the fear of a fie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry furnace made them do any thing: Shall not then the fear of thoſe eternal flames, the fear of this Day, wherein God will reveal all wrath without any mercy to the wicked man, Shall not this turn thee out of thy wayes? Shall not this make thee with bitterneſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wail
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:170542:117"/> thy former luſts? <hi>Deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damus in infernum viventes, ne deſcendamus morientes,</hi> Be not ſo enſlaved to the Devil, as to ſay, Give me my pleaſures, my profits to day, though to morrow I be in the grave, I be in hell. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, was a wicked ſpeech in <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom</hi>'s time, which he zealouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inveighed againſt; yet is it not ſtill the voice of every pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane man, Give me that which is ſweet or pleaſant, though it choak me? But more (particularly) becauſe of this Day of Judgement, take heed in theſe reſpects:</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Beware of living in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret ſins, ſecret uncleanneſs,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:170542:118"/> ſecret lying, bribing, or unjuſt wayes, for this will be the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent work of the Day of Judgement, to bring all ſecret things to light; The Day of Judgement is <hi>Judicare malè ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicata, &amp; non judicata,</hi> thoſe ſins which for the ſecretneſs the Magiſtrate cannot judge, at the Day of Judgement will then be moſt eminently and ſignally judged by God: That will be the Day when thoſe ſins, which no neighbour, no wife, no friend in the world knows, ſhall be diſcovered and judged; <hi>Whatſoever is ſaid,</hi> or done, <hi>in ſecret, ſhall be preacht upon the houſe-top. Whoremongers and adulterers
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:170542:118"/> God will judge.</hi> Why will God judge them? Becauſe ſuch ſins are ſo ſecretly committed, that the Magiſtrate cannot pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh them. Flatter not thy ſelf with ſecretneſs, ſeeing there will be a Day of Judgement, but live ſo uprightly and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely, that if thou hadſt <hi>Gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges</hi> ring, which they fable would make a man inviſible, yet thou wouldſt with <hi>Joſeph</hi> ſay, <hi>How can I do this and ſinne against God?</hi> The more craft, ſubtilty and ſecrecy there is in a ſinne, the greater is thy wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs, as appeareth <hi>Joſhua</hi> 7.9. That <hi>wedge of gold</hi> was a tongue indeed, as the word ſignifieth. Sometimes even in
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:170542:119"/> this life, God judgeth ſecret ſins to make them confeſs them, and bring them to light, how much rather at that great Day. <hi>Prov.</hi> 5.14.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Becauſe of this Day of Judgement, take heed of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counting any ſins little, as if they were venial, for at this great Day, even thoſe ſhall be judged, as well as the greateſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 12.36. <hi>We muſt give an account of every idle word at the Day of Judgement.</hi> It is true, Some learned men, becauſe of the Context, do poſitively determine, That the idle word is no leſs than the ſin againſt the holy Ghoſt; but more probably our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:170542:119"/> argueth from the leſs to the greater: If of an idle word a man ſhall give account, how much more of that blaſphemy againſt the holy Ghoſt? Do not then charge men as too ſtrict or preciſe, when they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to abſtain from idle thoughts and idle words, that they dare not give themſelves that licence which others take, for theſe are indictable as well as great ſins; an idle word will damn thee as well as ſinfull actions, if not repented of; For what are the apoſtate An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels adjudged to eternal tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and reſerved in thoſe chains of darkneſs? Was it for any more than proud
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:170542:120"/> thoughts, and the very firſt alſo? There cannot be any little ſinne, no more than a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle God, or a little hell, or a little damnation, in ſome ſenſe; <hi>Futurum Judicium eſt, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ucides,</hi> ſaid a devout An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, to one whom he ſaw laughing; If a man ſhould have no other ſinne, but an idle word, or an idle thought, yet at the Day of Judgement this would eternally caſt him, for this needeth the bloud of Chriſt to waſh it away, as well as other ſins: But wo, and a thouſand times wo to us, becauſe of this Day; For what are all our Feaſtings? What are all our meals, but
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:170542:120"/> ſo many idle words? What are all our meetings, our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panyings together, but ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny idle words?</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Becauſe of this Day of Judgement, therefore in a particular manner take heed of ſins of omiſſion; Do not bleſs thy ſelf with a priva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Righteouſneſs, <hi>Lord, I bleſs thee I am no drunkard, no extortioner, nor like this Publican;</hi> It is not a Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, but a Poſitive Holineſs which this Day will enquire after. Thus you may reade of that ſolemn proceſs at the Day of Judgement, <hi>Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>th.</hi> 25.42, 43. <hi>I was in priſon, and ye viſited me not,</hi> &amp;c.
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:170542:121"/> all is for omiſſion; It's not for ſins committed, you rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed me, defrauded me, you perſecuted me, you put me into priſon, but the omiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of what they ſhould have done, was that which did condemn them. Now how dreadful will the Day of Judgement be, even in this reſpect to moſt men? How little do they conſider their Negative, their Privative ſinnes? thou comforteſt thy ſelf, becauſe thou art none of the groſs poſitive ſinners in the world; but what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion will fall upon thee, when God ſhall enquire about thy omiſſions? Thou doſt
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:170542:121"/> not curſe or ſwear, but thou prayeſt not, thou calleſt not upon God privately, or in thy Family, thou doſt not oppoſe all ſuch who are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciouſly ſet againſt thoſe who fear God, thou art but a meer Negative Chriſtian, thou doſt not reprove ſinne, thou doſt not puniſh ſinne, thou art not zealous for the holy wayes of God: Oh conſider, this not doing will damn thee, as well as ſinful doing, and in this God will make ſpecial enquiry; How many Talents hath God gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven thee, and thou haſt not improved them? How ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny bleſſed advantages for
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:170542:122"/> good have been vouchſaft, and thou haſt omitted them? as Divines ſay, <hi>Plures ſunt gratiae privativae, quam poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivae,</hi> ſo <hi>Plura ſunt peceata pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vativa quam poſitiva.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. Becauſe there is a Day of Judgement, take heed of Hypocriſie, of carnal and corrupt Ends in the profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of Chriſts way, for that Day will eſpecially bring the <hi>Jehues,</hi> and the <hi>Judaſſes</hi> to light, who though they may for a ſeaſon do the will of God, yet becauſe not for Gods ſake, not upon pure and righteous motives, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the great work of that Day will be to unmask ſuch,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:170542:122"/> and make them naked, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.9, 10. This made <hi>Paul</hi> walk with ſuch integrity, not ſeeking himſelf in the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry of the Word, <hi>becauſe we muſt all appear before the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſeat of Chriſt,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, we muſt be thorowly made manifeſt and tranſparent; Now it is hardly known who is an hypocrite, and who is ſincere, who is truly for God, and who in pretence only, who is <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, and who is <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, but then the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels and thoughts of the heart will be diſcloſed. That is remarkable, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.5. <hi>Paul</hi> did not matter other mens judgements, yea he did not
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:170542:123"/> judge himſelf, becauſe the Day of Judgement will finde out more evil, more hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie, more ſinfulneſs than ever we thought of. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.14. The hypocrites are ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized with fearfulneſs, <hi>Who among us ſhall dwell with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring fire?</hi> A man that is carried by falſe motives in Religion, hath hell heated ſeven times hotter for him; Hence the expreſſion for an heavy damnation, is to <hi>have a portion with the hypocrites, Matth.</hi> 24.51. It was the ſpeech of that famous Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour for the Heathens, <hi>Syma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus,</hi> pleading for the Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Heatheniſh Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:170542:123"/> when urged to become a Chriſtian, in a ſcoffing man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, <hi>Fac me Epiſcopum Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manum, &amp; ero Chriſtianus,</hi> Are not many too real, what this Heathen was in pretence? Help me to profit, to prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and I will turn religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; but pray thou for truth in the inward parts.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Laſtly, Let the thoughts of this Day moderate thy ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite to the great things of this world, to wealth, honours, places of truſt and charge, for as theſe things do increaſe, ſo their account will be greater at that Day: Oh that I had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver been a Magiſtrate, will one ſay! Oh that I had never been
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:170542:124"/> a Miniſter, will another ſay! We ſhall be then as ready to ſhake off thoſe burdens, as now we are to put them on. Let this therefore ſatisfie thee, if I have leſs, my account will be leſs at that great Day.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
